<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prophecies of Christopher Kotterus, Christiana Poniatovia, Nicholas Drabicius Three famous German prophets, foretelling forty years agoe this present invasion of the Turks into the Empire of Germany, and the events that will ensue. The miraculous conversion of the great Turk, and the translating of the Bible into the Turkish language. Predictions concerning the Pope, Emperor, and King of France, with the sudden destruction of the Popish religion in the year 1666. Presaging also the uniting of all religions into one visible church, and how that church shall be governed by Bishops, &amp;c. Many of the prophecies were very much desired by the late King of Bohemia, and were presented to him by the learned and eminent Protestant divine Comenius, and by him made publick. Translated out of the Latine by R. C. Gent. Licensed and entered according to order.</title>
            <title>Lux in tenebris. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70412</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834837_39410</idno>
  <idno type="VID">39410</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2288800267</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K750A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23099</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834837</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99834837e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 638:2, 1953:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prophecies of Christopher Kotterus, Christiana Poniatovia, Nicholas Drabicius Three famous German prophets, foretelling forty years agoe this present invasion of the Turks into the Empire of Germany, and the events that will ensue. The miraculous conversion of the great Turk, and the translating of the Bible into the Turkish language. Predictions concerning the Pope, Emperor, and King of France, with the sudden destruction of the Popish religion in the year 1666. Presaging also the uniting of all religions into one visible church, and how that church shall be governed by Bishops, &amp;c. Many of the prophecies were very much desired by the late King of Bohemia, and were presented to him by the learned and eminent Protestant divine Comenius, and by him made publick. Translated out of the Latine by R. C. Gent. Licensed and entered according to order.</title>
                  <title>Lux in tenebris. English.</title>
                  <author>Kotter, Christoph, d. 1647. aut</author>
                  <author>Poniatowska, Krystyna, 1610-1644. aut</author>
                  <author>Drabik, Mikuláš, 1588-1671. aut</author>
                  <author>Comenius, Johann Amos, 1592-1670.</author>
                  <author>Codrington, Robert, 1601-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition corrected and amended.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 115 p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Pawlet at the sign of the Bible in Chancery-lane, near the Inner-Temple Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Lux in tenebris.</note>
                  <note>The words "Christopher .. Drabicius." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Prophesies of the Turke, Emperour, Pope, and France.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:39410:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>figure of a Turk holding Bible and scimitar</figDesc>
                  <head>A The greate Turke and his Cruelty in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many: B his Conversion by the Bible C The Downfall of the Pope and his Religion in 1666</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39410:1"/>
            <p>PROPHECIES Of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Christopher Kotterus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Christiana Poniatovia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nicholas Drabicius.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Three Famous <hi>German</hi> Prophets, Foretelling Forty years agoe this present Invasion of the Turks into the Empire of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Events that will ensue. The miraculous Conversion of the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> and the Translating of the Bible into the Turkish Language.</p>
            <p>Predictions concerning the Pope, Emperor, and King of <hi>France,</hi> with the sudden destruction of the Popish Religion in the year 1666.</p>
            <p>Presaging also the uniting of all Religions into one visible Church, and how that Church shall be Governed by Bishops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many of these Prophecies were very much desired by the late King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and were presented to him By the Learned and Eminent Protestant Divine <hi>Comenius,</hi> and by him made publick.</p>
            <p>Translated out of the Latine by <hi>R. C.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Licensed and Entered according to Order.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The second Edition Corrected and amended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Pawlet</hi> at the Sign of the Bible in <hi>Chancery-lane,</hi> near the Inner-Temple Gate, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39410:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39410:2"/>
            <head>To the most Illustrious and most Excellent PRINCE RUPERT, Count Palatine of <hi>Rhine</hi> AND Duke of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Highness,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat the King your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Memory, did so often desire to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use, do here of their own accord, with much Humility ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress themselves to kiss your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness<hi>'s</hi> hand. They are the Prophecies of <hi>Kotterus,</hi> now in English, which many years since were presented to the King your Father in <hi>Holland,</hi> and were most acceptable to his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39410:3"/>
            <p>I have annexed to them the Visions and Prophecies of two other famous Personages, whose Memories do yet flourish in <hi>Silesia, Moravia</hi> and <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and their inspirations tending so often to the advancement of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty and Glory of your Royal Family, I thought I was obliged, as well by Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as Gratulation, to give your Highness (who are the Mirrour both of Arms and Arts) a sight of these Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sults of Providence, assuring you, that what are the Presages of three Prophets, is the constant Expectation, and the Prayer of Him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highnesses<lb/> most humble and<lb/> most devoted Servant,</hi>
                  <lb/> Robert Codrington.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39410:3"/>
            <head>THE PROPHECIES, Of the three famous and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Prophets in <hi>Germany,</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling long ago, the present in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion of the <hi>Turks</hi> into the Empire of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the events that will ensue.</head>
            <head type="sub">As also Praedictions concerning the Emperour, Pope, and King of <hi>France,</hi> with the conversi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any Learned and Reverend Personages, and some of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church themselves, have foretold the Ruine and the Downfal of the Pope: amongst whom hath been <hi>Joachimus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Calabria,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:39410:4"/> who flourished in the 13 age after the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cension of our Saviour,<note place="margin">The Popish Priests themselves have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told his overthrow.</note> and <hi>Robertus Gallus,</hi> who by many Orthodox Divines, is recorded to have seen the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> in the form of a Dragon.</p>
            <p>Not long after him, lived <hi>Johannes de Rupe Scissa,</hi> whom Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth committed to prison for preaching against the pride and avarice of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and presaging a Reformation to come: There was contemporary with him a certain Monk, named <hi>Hayabalus,</hi> who proved the Pope with his Cardinals to be Antichrist.</p>
            <p>After him lived <hi>Theodorick</hi> Bishop of <hi>Croatia,</hi> and a Virgin called <hi>Mechtild,</hi> who both of them prophesied the ruin of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Reformation of the Church: In that Age of the world or presently afterwards lived <hi>John Hus,</hi> the first Reformer of the Church in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> who suffered the flames of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom at <hi>Constance,</hi> whom God at that present inspired with the Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, insomuch that at the stake, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced these words; <hi>After one hundred years you shal answer to God and to my self: Now you do roast a Goose,</hi> (for <hi>Hus</hi> in the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39410:4"/> tongue signifies a Goose) <hi>but a Swan shall come after me, over whom the Fire shall have no power,</hi> which prophecy was afterwards fulfilled in <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there were none that prophesied the fall of the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> more fully or more plainly, than <hi>Christopher Kotterus,</hi> and a Virgin descended of a noble Family, named <hi>Christina Poniatovia,</hi> together with a third Person, whose name was <hi>Nicolaus Drabitius,</hi> of whose wonderful Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we shall in order give you a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as it was the first, that did shake of its obedience to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> so it was the first, that felt the fury and the flames of Persecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the two great Professors of the Truth <hi>John Hus</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> of <hi>Prague,</hi> in the years 1414, and 1415 being both brought before the Council were both condemned to the flames of Martyrdome: and the Empire, of <hi>Germany</hi> by the sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion of the Pope, being stirred up to make Warre upon <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Sword devoured throughout <hi>Bohemia,</hi> for the space of seventeen years. After this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the persecution by the Council of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39410:5"/>
               <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Orders and Edicts from the Emperour, were issued out for the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter destroying of the reformed Religion, and the banishing and suppressing the true Professors of it.</p>
            <p>But God left not himself without wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, for by extraordinary Revelations, he gave advertisements by some peculiar persons of wonderfull Revolutions to come; as of the Destruction of the Great Beast,<note place="margin">By the great Beast is meant the Empire of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and he who rides on it the Pope.</note> by which the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> was portended, and of the fal of the proud Person that did sit upon it.</p>
            <p>In the year 1616 <hi>Christopher Kotterus</hi> foretold the great war to insue in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> at what time <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi> were in a most quiet condition; neither was there the lest suspition of any trouble to appear. The truth, of this praediction, <hi>Germany</hi> found thirty years afterwards, and shall yet finde the burden of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy to grow upon her with greater vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence And indeed what part is there in <hi>Europe,</hi> which doth now enjoy so great a Peace as <hi>Germany</hi> did at that time? two years afterwards <hi>Kotterus</hi> brought this Revelation to the chief Magistrate of <hi>Sprotovia,</hi> the war in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> being new
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39410:5"/> begun: but <hi>Germany</hi> at that time did think her self secure, much more did other Nations, who thought themselves more removed from it.</p>
            <p>This Universall trouble, to be all the world over, was again presaged by him in the year 1620, when there was a Peace every where but in <hi>Bohemia:</hi> he presaged that a time will come, when many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of Horse should march from the East to the North, and from the North to the West, into the upper parts of <hi>Germany;</hi> and that the Army should be divided into seven bodies, according to the number of the Commanders.</p>
            <p>He shewed what would be the event of that most bloody war; which is, that God, according to his mercy, wisedome, &amp; power should wonderfully glorifie his Name by the Conversion of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The great Turk to be a Convert after his Victories in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and to turn Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</note> &amp; that this Conversion should admirably begin with a great Monarch of the East; whose example (he himselfe being the most eminent person on the Earth) other Nations should follow with him; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing by reason of his great infirmity, not onely as he is a Man, but as ignorant of the worship of the true God, that God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39410:6"/> shall make his power visible to him by many great Miracles; at which he being astonished, shall become a Convert unto Christ.</p>
            <p>He proceeds, by foretelling what will be the successe by the Atchievements of these Warriours; which is, that by their valour the Moon and the Lyon shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a greater splendour. By the Moon, most commonly the Church is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, and sometimes more particularly some principal defender of it: Moreover, these men of War shall overthrow a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Tree, wonderful for its height, that is to say, some great House, or Prince, most eminent for the present, and more conspicious than all others, as was the Tree of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which is spoken of the conversion of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> or the Nations, is further illustrated by the Embleme of a Bell of a stupendious magnitude, whose Sound was heard over all the Earth; <hi>That is,</hi> The Gospel shall be preached unto all Nations: And, to the hearing of God's Word, men are commonly called by the sound of a Bell.</p>
            <p>From Revelations in general, <hi>Kotterus</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39410:6"/> doth descend to Revelations in particular to one person, To <hi>Frederick</hi> the late King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> where what is spoken of him hath relation to his whole Family; which in these words he doth expresly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, <hi>Fredericus initium fecit, posteri continuare debent. Frederick</hi> did begin it, his posterity are to continue it. And two things in this Prophecy of him are remarkable:</p>
            <p>The first is, that by his overthrow there shall no peace in <hi>Germany,</hi> ensue upon it, but a greater flame of War shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise; not for the Interest or the Cause of <hi>Frederick;</hi> but that God will raise an Army, by which to punish the sins of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> Which afterwards came to pass by the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> by <hi>Tilly, Wallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steyn,</hi> and others; and afterwards by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and their Confederates: And which shall shortly more violently be prosecuted by the Armies of the East.</p>
            <p>The calamity which <hi>Germany</hi> shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for the space of those thirty years,<note place="margin">By the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the East, is meant the Turks.</note> shall be but little; and inconsiderable to those unspeakable sorrows which the multitude of her <hi>Eastern</hi> adversaries shall bring upon her; for God hath put the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39410:7"/> Rod of his present wrath into the hand of the Lord of the Eastern Nations, and <hi>hath commanded him to make war against it.</hi> And moreover, this Prophet doth affirm, that he is commanded by God to declare unto all the Lords, Earls, Princes, and Potentates of the Empire, to look unto themselves, if they would avoid the terrible hand of this Executioner; and to take care, lest they come under his power and drink of their own Blood: And this doth enforce him to cry out aloud; <hi>Woe unto Caesar, woe unto the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces! for there shall come upon you Hunger, and Famine, Warre and the Effusion of Blood. O You, the Potentates of</hi> Germany, <hi>who now, with pampered Horses, are carried in rich and stately Coaches, take heed least the Birds of the Air do carry your Bodies in their strutting gorges over Seas, and Rivers, into other Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Calamity of the <hi>Swedish</hi> war is but the prologue only to this dreadfull Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is committed to the charge of the Governour of the East, to execute against you: for the more merciful <hi>Swedes</hi> did leave the Nobles of <hi>Germany</hi> in their dignities;<note place="margin">The Turks</note> but these Eastern Adversaries
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39410:7"/> shall not give the least respect unto their Dignity or Greatnesse. It is high time therefore to provide for their safety, by a thorough repentance, which is needfull indeed to every one, who will be carefull to avoid the Fire of Hell.</p>
            <p>As to the time, for the final ruine of the Pope of <hi>Rome; Kotterus,</hi> in the eighth Chapter of his Praedictions, and the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth verse, doth set down four num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, 1621, 1622, 1623, 1624.<note place="margin">The Time of the final ruin of the Pope of Rome.</note> And saith of them, <hi>That these four shall consumate those things which God hath decreed in his Councell,</hi> And in the eighth verse he saith of them, <hi>Three wonderful things shall come to passe in the eyes of Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There shall be a Triall for the disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Hipocrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>One shall fall from his Throne, and never again recover it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Pope, with all his proud Train, shall be humbled in the Dust, and be consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The better to understand the meaning, of these numbers, there is more to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered.</p>
            <p>First, From whence that Number doth begin.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:39410:8"/>
            <p>Secondly, How it is placed in the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, How those three wonderfull things may be contained in the four num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers already mentioned.</p>
            <p>To the first: <hi>From whence, or from what year the beginning of this Numeration ought to be,</hi> is expresly mentioned in the fifth Chapter, and the one and thirtieth Verse; which is from the taking of <hi>Prague</hi> which was at the end of the year 1620. The following year therefore, which is the year 1621. is to be the first in those four Numbers. And this must be the <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus à quo,</hi> or the Term from which we must begin, <hi>viz.</hi> the year 1621.</p>
            <p>To the second, <hi>How this number is to be placed.</hi> In the placing of this number, the <hi>German</hi> Protestants, after the taking of the City of <hi>Prague,</hi> did commit a great Errour, and conceived that all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions of the Warre would have ended with those four years, 1621, 1622, 1623, 1624. and when the year 1624 was past, and the calamities of the War did still in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, they were extreamly troubled at it; and afterwards out of the inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate desire of a speedy deliverance from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39410:8"/> their oppression, they would snatch at any other number, but always at the shortest. And this they did without any ground at all; which was the reason that the Event did not answer their Expectation. But now, on the better observation of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of <hi>Kotterus,</hi> concerning this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the Spirit, <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>vers.</hi> 10. hath expresly shewed how those numbers are to be composed; which is to be done thus: by the due ordering of the last Cyphers of those four numbers.</p>
            <p>
               <list type="sum">
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>2</item>
                  <item>3</item>
                  <item>4</item>
                  <item ana="#role_total">10</item>
               </list> In this number, the Spirit saith, there lyeth a mystery, which is 10.</p>
            <p>And this will serve as a Key for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter understanding of the other Numbers; and most probable it is, that the rest of those four numbers are in the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to be computed, and to stand under one another as these last numbers of 1, 2, 3, 4. which make ten. As thus.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39410:9"/>
            <p>The last number contains
<list>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
               </list> which makes 4. The next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it,
<list>
                  <item>2</item>
                  <item>2</item>
                  <item>2</item>
                  <item>2</item>
               </list> which makes 8.</p>
            <p>The third number containeth
<list>
                  <item>6</item>
                  <item>6</item>
                  <item>6</item>
                  <item>6</item>
               </list> which makes 24 which 4, 8, and 24, being put together, do make 36; and with the first ten above specified 46.</p>
            <p>The tumults therefore of war were to continue 46 years; which if you adde to the year 1620, when <hi>Prague</hi> was lost, there will arise the year 1666, which number 666 is mentioned in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyps. Neither is it any thing unusual to men to passe by the greatest number unmenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as being most known. For Example-sake; If I demand of one, in what year he was born; and he makes answer, In six hundred and three, I presently collect that the year one thousand is implicitely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood. The same number 666 doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39410:9"/> in many other places of his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>As to the third thing, necessary to be understood, which is, <hi>How those three won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things, are contained in those four numbers, and what is the proportion and harmony,</hi> that thereby is meant. You are to consider, that it is usual in <hi>Daniel,</hi> but most frequent in the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> in praedictions to make mention of <hi>a time, two times, and halfe a time;</hi> the like is to be found in <hi>Kotterus;</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>It will follow therefore, that the numbers
<list type="sum">
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>2</item>
                  <item>3</item>
                  <item>4</item>
                  <item ana="#role_total">10</item>
               </list> do signifie one time.</p>
            <p>The second and third numbers put together
<list type="sum">
                  <item>62</item>
                  <item>62</item>
                  <item>62</item>
                  <item>62</item>
                  <item ana="#role_total">24:8:</item>
               </list> do signifie two times.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:39410:10"/>
            <p>The first number
<list type="sum">
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item>1</item>
                  <item ana="#role_total">4</item>
               </list> doth signifie halfe a time. which all put together do make 46, as hath been already shewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The first time</hi> therefore are <hi>ten years,</hi> which from the year 1620, after the taking of <hi>Prague,</hi> do run up into 1630: In this first ten years, there ought to come to pass the <hi>first wonderfull thing</hi> (as above is specified) <hi>which is the time of Triall for the discovery of Hipocrites;</hi> and this, in the Eyes of all men, was fulfilled; when by the continual victories of <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandus Caesar</hi> for ten years together; by military insultations and oppressions; by Imprisonments, and Proscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other kind of torments, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Professors being troubled in their minds, did startle from the known Truth, and some others, who had been haters and persecutors of the truth were converted to it, and became true Believers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The two times,</hi> which do arise out of the addition of the four two's, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39410:10"/> four sixes, to wit, 32 years, do shew in what time the second wonderfull thing shall come to pass, which wonder is <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>vers.</hi> 6. <hi>There shall one fall from his throne, neither shall he ever recover it again, viz.</hi> In those 32 years, the beginning of which 32 years, is to be taken from the year 1630, in which the number of the first time, <hi>to wit,</hi> of the ten years, ended; therefore in the year 1630, his throne, who is to fall must begin to be shaken with War, and to totter untill the final e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of it. And this concussion of it is to continue for the space of two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, that is, for the two times.</p>
            <p>This was fulfilled, when in the year 1630 <hi>Gustavus</hi> King of <hi>Swedland</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into <hi>Germany;</hi> &amp; not long afterwards did, first of all, give a great blow to the falling throne, having overthrown <hi>Tilly</hi> at <hi>Leipswich</hi> with his invincible Army.</p>
            <p>This war, or the animosities of it, is to continue for the space of two and thirty years: for although the peace at <hi>Osnabrook</hi> did give a little respite, yet it did put no end unto it. Therefore this peace, <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 50, is said to continue <hi>but for half an hour:</hi> and indeed how short a time is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39410:11"/> that; they, who labour with great toyle all the day, do finde but a little refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the compasse of halfe an hour, and <hi>Germany</hi> did not long enjoy this Peace.<note place="margin">Rome to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown in four years which are already begun.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Halfe of a time</hi> doth follow, <hi>to wit,</hi> the four years, for the destruction of the Pope, and the Rabble that attend upon him. Now to bring, so great a change upon all <hi>Italy,</hi> and to subdue <hi>Rome,</hi> and all about it, in the compasse of four years, is no long time; it doth not therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from, but rather confirme the truth expressed in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> Babylon <hi>shall fall like a Millstone;</hi> and God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this great work by men, who had need of time to perform what they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, and not by Angels, who need no tract of time for the performance of the execution committed to their charge: Moreover the Almighty in his words doth allow some space of time, that the slow workings of men, might the better consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it, and more thoroughly perform it. If therefore so great a Power and Majesty, as the Pope doth challenge to himself, shall fall unto the Ground in the compasse of four short years, who will not wonder at it?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39410:11"/>
            <p>Parallels to these three wonders, are those three things, which follow in this Prophecy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The First, there shall be taken from the Beast his sight and understanding.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, his strength, power, and pride shall be taken from him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, his glory and splendor shall perish.</p>
            <p>It is most certain, that by the Beast, the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> is understood, as is expresly to be seen, in the tenth <hi>chapter</hi> of this Prophecy <hi>ver.</hi> 40, 41, 42. But the taking away of the sight and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Beast was fulfilled from the year 1620, to the year 1630 by the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual victories of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the second: for after the loss of <hi>Prague, Mansfield, Durlach, Karmour, Bethlem, Gabor,</hi> the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Weymar,</hi> and whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver else did oppose him, did only serve to make his Conquests the more illustrious, with which being puffed up he made War upon the Consciences of men, by imposing on them to follow and believe, that which they ought not to give consent unto: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blindness was, that in the year 1630 he undertook a Warre in <hi>Italy;</hi> by which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39410:12"/> he made the King of <hi>France</hi> his enemy; and to this pertains the judgement of a great Baron of <hi>Moravia</hi> (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise a great friend and follower of the Emperours) made of him when ever he heard, that his forces had taken <hi>Prague:</hi> This (said he) will be the beginning of the Ruine of the House of <hi>Austria.</hi> The standers by inquiring after the meaning of this paradox he made answer to them; <hi>I am not ignorant how insolently the House of</hi> Austria <hi>do abuse their victories, which other Princes will not indure; neither God himself, if he shall go about to oppose his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The second Parallel is, that his pride and his strength shall be taken from him, and that within the positive terme of the <hi>two times,</hi> which was fulfilled by the many victories of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> from the year 1630, to the year 1632.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, there shall be taken from the Beast his glory and splender: In which praediction the Pope as well as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is implied; and this shall happen from the year 1662, to the year 1663, which is the terme of the <hi>halfe time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He concludes, happy is the man, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39410:12"/> shall live to this time: for fourteen years afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> in the year 1680, the Nations and People being reduced into the lap of the Church, the building of the new <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is immediately to succeed it. Concerning which <hi>Kotterus</hi> hath many great and Glorious Revelations,</p>
            <p>But herein the error of the Millenaries, concerning the bodily return of Christ, and his reigning on earth in his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son before the end of the World, is to be reproved: In the same manner, the bodily resurrection of the Martyrs and of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing of the Kingdom of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and other carnall Pomps and delights (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto the dreams of the <hi>Jews</hi> and of <hi>Cerinthus</hi>) are to be rejected; Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, that Christ shall reign here in his Power, and the Gospel of Truth be most gloriously propagated, may appear in many places of the holy Text.</p>
            <p>Having given you some light, for the better understanding of these Prophets, before we descend unto the Prophecies themselves: we shall in this place, give you a brief account of their Lives, as we have received it from <hi>Comenius,</hi> who hath been elaborate in them. We shall begin
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39410:13"/> with the Life and Prophecies of the first; and descend to the other two as they do follow in time and order.</p>
            <div type="biography">
               <head>The Life and Prophecies of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stopher Kotterus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Ministers of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> being banished from thence, in the year 1624, by the Edict of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the second, at that time Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Germany; Johannes Comenius,</hi> who compiled this History of these three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, was forced to forsake his Charge of the Ministery of the Gospell in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and to flie for his Religion and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, into <hi>Silesia;</hi> which at that time, was famous, for her Charity to the true professors of the Gospel of Christ. Here he first understood, of the Visions and Prophecies of <hi>Christopher Kotterus;</hi> to which at the first, he gave more wonder than belief; but being much incouraged and comforted to understand thereby, what great deliverance God, in his good time, would give unto his Church, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined with himself to empoly more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39410:13"/> time and Circumspection in examining the truth of the Prophet, and his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to which purpose having acquainted himself with divers Reverend Divines, he communicated this businesse to them, which so strangely did affect him: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more fully satisfied by them of the truth of it, he translated the Copy of the Visions and Prophecies into the Bohemian tongue; which not long afterwards, for the Novelty and Wonder of it, was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated by another, into the German tongue. In the mean time <hi>Comenius,</hi> understanding that <hi>Kotterus</hi> lived at that time in a City called <hi>Sprotta,</hi> which was not far from the place where he did lead a banished life, he resolved with himself to make a journey on purpose thither, to be better informed of the Man, and his Revelations.</p>
               <p>Being come to <hi>Sprotta</hi> in <hi>Silesia,</hi> he found the House, but could not find the person of <hi>Kotterus;</hi> for, at that time, he was sent for to <hi>Berlin</hi> by <hi>Willhelmus,</hi> Prince Elector, and Marquess of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> who being much affected at his Prophecies, was transported with a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate desire to see him, He was there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39410:14"/> strictly examined by <hi>Pelargus, Superatten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant General</hi> of the Churches of the whole Marquisate; and by Doctor <hi>Fusselius,</hi> chief chaplain to the Elector, to know by what Spirit he did write: who both, being ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the excellent answers he did give them, did dismisse him with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, his Prophecies being dispersed in <hi>Silesia, Bohemia,</hi> and in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> in printed Copies, and in Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scripts the Fame of this great Prophet, arrived at the Ear of <hi>Frederick,</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> who, the City of <hi>Prague</hi> being lost, and the war unhappily managed in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> was at that time in <hi>Holland</hi> with his Royal Consort <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Daughter to <hi>James</hi> the first King of <hi>England.</hi> And having heretofore seen <hi>Kotterus</hi> at <hi>Wrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tislaue,</hi> and discoursed there with him; he had a great disire to peruse the entire Book of his Prophecies: he therefore did send an Expresse to his own Mother <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana Austriaca,</hi> who lived then at <hi>Berlin,</hi> with her Daughter, the Electresse of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> to procure them for him.</p>
               <p>The Care and Charge of this was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39410:14"/> by the Queen Mother to <hi>Ladislaus de Zerotim</hi> Pro-Marquesse of <hi>Moravia,</hi> by whose procurement a copy of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies was accurately written, and the book was bound up most richly; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prevented himselfe by sicknesse, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired <hi>Commenius</hi> to take the pains to carry it to the King in <hi>Holland,</hi> which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he did; and having gained accesse by the means of the chiefest of his Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, Doctor <hi>Altingius,</hi> he made his Addresse unto him in these following words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>May it please your excellent Majesty,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Know in this great tryall of your Faith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Comenius</hi> his Speech to the late King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> concerning these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies</note> and Patience no divine Comforts can be wanting to you; and that you may say with the Prophet <hi>David, Unlesse thy Law, O Lord had been my comfort,</hi> &amp;c. But since our good GOD doth never fail to send com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort unto those, even by extraordinary means who are afflicted for the Truth; of which (if ever in any Age) those many wonders may be numbred; which, both in Heaven and Earth have been seen in this. As also some Revelations made by certain Persons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted credit, declaring wonderfull things
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39410:15"/> of the sudden mutation of Affairs in the world: and, amongst those more especially <hi>Kotterus</hi> of <hi>Sprotta</hi> in <hi>Silesia,</hi> who was present with your Majesty at <hi>Wrattislaue,</hi> and with his own mouth declared some of them unto you: Whose Prophecies since they are now recorded in writing, and your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, with your posterity and other Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do seem to be much interested in them; It was thought a great fault in those who had the custody of them, not to prefer them to your Majesties observance; not that any Necessity is imposed on your most Excellent Majesty precisely to believe them, but that they may be preserved for a testimonie to times to come in a safe Library; that so if the passages herein contained be fulfilled, and made manifest, no man may suspect or calumniate the Truth thereof, As also that thereby we may wait on the Divine Providence for the disposing and ordering of such things to their design'd Events. For, if we despise not to understand Political Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, or Astrological Predictions, or the Conjectures of Wise men concerning the imminent mutation of Affairs, Why should we neglect these things proceeding from a higher Principle? Care hath been taken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39410:15"/> therefore, that a Copy of them should be transcribed from the Original, which I here do most humbly present unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The King having taken the Book into his hand, and looking upon it, said, <hi>What! Is it of so great a Bulk?</hi> For it was of roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Paper, and folded into a <hi>quarto,</hi> and written in a very fair and legible letter. After he had opened it, and observed the picture of a man standing in the midst of a great army, to whom a golden Book was offered; He demanded, what was the meaning of it: and answer being made, that <hi>The Conversion of the Turks was thereby presaged.</hi> What! <hi>And must they be converted also,</hi> said the King? And commanded <hi>Comenius</hi> to give him the scope of the Prophecies throughout all the Book; which being done, the King said, <hi>GOD grant a deliverance to the Church from all her persecutions, and a propagation of the Gospel amongst all the unbelievers;</hi> and having spoke those words he graciously dismissed him.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1626. <hi>Kotterus</hi> took a journey into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> being invited thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by many of the Nobility, and some
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39410:16"/> of the Reformed Ministers, who privately where protected by them in that Country. Continuing amongst them for a certain time he resolved with himself to travel to <hi>Clogovia,</hi> although he was much disswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from it by his friends. Here it pleased God, that in the year 1637. on the 2. of <hi>January</hi> he was discovered, apprehended, and hurried to prison; where he lived for the space of three months in extream mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery; and had never come out of it with Life, had it not been by the sudden and most unexpected death of the Fiscal his greatest Enemy.</p>
               <p>But he being taken out of the world, <hi>Kotterus</hi> not long afterwards was taken out of prison; and being sentenced to stand in publick on a market day with a paper on his forehead to shew the nature of his offence; as a false Prophet, he became a spectacle to the whole City, for the space of an hour; which being expired, one of the Officers brought him unto the Gates of the City, and commanded him to come no more into it, nor into any other place in the Dominions of the Empire, under the pains of death.</p>
               <p>He departed therefore into <hi>Lusatia,</hi> at
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39410:16"/> that time under the jurisdiction of the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> were he spent the rest of his Life; with his Wife and Family in great tranquillity, and was translated unto a better Life in the year 1647.</p>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Visions and Revelations of <hi>Christopher Kotterus,</hi> concerning the ruine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, together with the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ON the 11. day of <hi>June.</hi> in the year of our Lord 1616, there first of all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared an Angel in the shape of a man to <hi>Kotterus</hi> as he was going forth, and said unto him; <hi>Friend, stay a little, I must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver something to you, which you must de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the Ecclesiastical and Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates. Kotterus,</hi> being amazed at this Summons and knowing not what to say, the Angel proceeded and told him, <hi>That the Anger of God was kindled against Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and that in fury he hastened to inflict punishment on them, unlesse they repented; &amp; above all things, he will punish them for their Pride and Impurity, and for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and of his Word.</hi> Having
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39410:17"/> spoke these words, the Angel vanished from his sight; but five days afterwards he appeared to him again, and repeated the same things.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="vision">
                  <head>The second Vision in the year <hi>1619. April 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>But <hi>Kotterus,</hi> being overcome by the counsel of some of his friends, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded him to the contrary, the Angel appeared to him again in the same form as before, and demanded of him, <hi>If he had performed what he had commanded him? Kotterus,</hi> not knowing what Answer to make, did stand like a dumb man; but the Angel lifting up his eyes to heaven, said, <hi>Not unto us, not unto us, but unto thy Name O Lord give the glory.</hi> And turning to <hi>Kotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> he said, <hi>Wherefore did you neglect to do as you were commāded?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Kotterus</hi> his call from God to the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Prophet.</note>
                     <hi>hath not Almighty God deserved better at your hands? It is he, who hath created you, redeemed you, and sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied you, and regenerated you to the hope of eternal life. It is he, who for your sake deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up his own Son to death: And do you refuse to speak a word or two for his sake, &amp; to offer up your self an Instrument for the performance of his work? I pronounce unto you, If you do it not, you shall have no quiet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39410:17"/> in your heart; and moreover, your name shall be blotted out of the Book of Life. Why are you afraid of Men, more light than the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spers of leaves blown by the wind, of whom indeed you shall receive a threefold censure?</hi> 1. <hi>Some of them shall threaten you.</hi> 2. <hi>Some of them shall admire you. And</hi> 3ly. <hi>Others shall give no regard unto you. But do you take heed that you lay not such things to your heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, the Spirit began to inform him, that the face of the present Times was partly <hi>cleer,</hi> and partly <hi>clowdy; Cleer</hi> and <hi>joyfull,</hi> because they are the Times of Grace, in which the light of the Divine Truth, hath shined upon men with so pure a splendour; <hi>Cloudy</hi> and <hi>sorrowful,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause men refuse to see this light, and had rather have their hearts darkned with Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Infidelity. At the last, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced; <hi>Ʋnlesse that men do earnestly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve, and endeavour to amend themselves, GOD will most grievously punish them with Fire, Sword, Famine, and Pestilence.</hi> And giving his right hand to <hi>Kotterus,</hi> he admonished him to put off all Fear, for no evill should come unto him; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he added, <hi>I will accelerate my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39410:18"/> word to perform it;</hi> and having said so, he vanished away. <hi>Koterus</hi> being left alone stood still at first, as being lost, in a great amazement: and presently afterwards, looking round about him, he beheld on the one side a Company cloathed in white, singing and rejoycing; and on the other side of him, a Rabble all in black, groaning and howling: and being amazed at this Vision, he made haste to his own house, and on the 9 of <hi>August,</hi> at a full meeting of the Senate of the City, he declared all these things unto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="vision">
                  <head>The third Vision, in the year, <hi>1620. Aug. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Angel that was seen before, did appear unto him again, and demanded of him, <hi>If he had dispatched that Errand which was committed to his charge.</hi> He made answer that he had; and that he was scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and laughed at for his pains.</p>
                  <p>The Angel admonished him to proceed without fear; for he had many more things to reveal unto him, concerning not onely men of an Inferiour Condition, but the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> himself. As first, <hi>That the Princes of the Empire should not so
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39410:18"/> headily rush into Armes, but rather abstain from the Effusion of Blood. And that God would take the Cause into his own Hands, and revenge the quarrel, by sending a roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lyon to devour his enemies, that not any foot-step of them should remain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Eight days afterwards he beheld a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle lifted above the Earth, and hanging in the Air, from whence he heard three Clocks like to one another in the sound, and every one of them striking eleven. At that time he understood not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, which was revealed unto him on the 16 of the same moneth following, <hi>viz. That in that Triangle, or threefold Dimension, he might behold the most holy Trinity; and by the uniformity of the sound of the three Clocks, he might acknowledge the unity of the Trinity; and that the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the 11th. Hour did admonish, It was high time to rise from the sleep of sin; because it is the 11th. Hour in which the Master of the Family went forth to hire Labourers into his Vineyard, and that not long after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he will sit down to give the wages to his Work-men,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He proceeded; that as the Priests of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Scribes and Pharisees were not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39410:19"/> converted at the miracles and passion of our Saviour; but the hearts of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were penetrated, so that one of them said, Either God Himself doth suffer, or the end of the World is at hand; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seeing him Crucified, did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be the Son of God. In the like manner, in the miracles within a short time to be wrought, especially in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> their hearts shall be neither tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,<note place="margin">The great Turk to be converted.</note> nor turned unto God: But a great Monarch of many Kingdoms shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted; who, abandoning the darknesse of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> shall receive the light of the Gospel Having uttered these words, he vanished.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>
                     <hi>December</hi> 1. 1620.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> having declared that which he was commanded by the Angel to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates,<note place="margin">The Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>Kotterus,</hi> before se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and Pastors.</note> he was referred by them to the Pastors and Ministers of the Church, who conjured him to declare unto them from whence he had these Revelations; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had feigned them himself, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them from some others, to disperse them abroad under the name of Visions: they advised him to consider thoroughly with himself, what, and how great things
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39410:19"/> they were he undertook, and how horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Crime he should be guilty of, if any deceit were in it. They propounded to him, unto how great a danger he should expose his Conscience, and pull upon himself the hatred and the anger both of God and Men; and hazard not onely his own life, but the lives of his Wife and Children. He being nothing terrified, nor startled at it, made answer, that he wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed All Curses and Imprecations, might fall upon him, if at any time he declared any thing, but that which he had heard and seen, and was commanded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal. That he never had any Revelation in his Sleeps, or Dreams; nor was there any thing feigned by him, a simple and an ignorant man; neither did he ever receive, or hear any thing from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man; but all things were exhibited to him by Voyce &amp; Vision. But whether this Spirit be good or bad, it lyeth not in his power to discern; and therefore he desired Counsel, and Information of them, whether any thing herein be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expresse word of GOD; but-for his part, he did believe, it was a good Spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="vision">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:39410:20"/>
                  <head>The fourth Vision, <hi>Decemb. 7. 1620.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Words and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of <hi>Kotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> at <hi>Wrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tislave</hi>
                     </note> On the seventh of <hi>Decemb.</hi> in the same year, he was commanded by the Spirit, to go to <hi>Wrattislaue,</hi> and to addresse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Into whose presence being admitted, he acquainted him (three other Princes being then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent with him) with the charge which he had from GOD to deliver to him. He concluded with these three Advices.</p>
                  <p>First, <hi>That he should make known to all his Enemies, how much his heart was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Peace:</hi> To which, if they were refractory, he told him, that God in his own time would raise up a mighty Army from the East against them; which should not be the Army of the King, but the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of GOD himself.</p>
                  <p>The second Advice was, <hi>That he dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently should look to his own safety, and beware of his private Enemies, who do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take his life from him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third was, <hi>That he should often call to mind the Example of the Patriarch</hi> Jacob, <hi>who had two such Enemies,</hi> Laban, <hi>and</hi> Esau.<note place="margin">The Kings answer to him.</note> Which being heard, the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> immediately made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; I take the first for a <hi>Command,</hi> the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39410:20"/> second for a <hi>Caution,</hi> and the third for a <hi>Mirrour,</hi> or a <hi>Glass.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>March 20. 1621.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>On the 20th. of <hi>March,</hi> in the year 1621. the Angel which appeared to him in former times, did lead him into a field, and demanded again of him. If he had performed what he was commanded, and encouraged him to continue in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Duty. He at that time told him, that GOD, from the beginning of the World, in five several wayes had exercised his Judgements upon Man-kind. The first of all, upon <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> whom with all their Progeny he did shut out of <hi>Paradise.</hi> The second on the whole World, which he destroyed with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge. The third Remarkable Judgement was, over the Cities of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah.</hi> The fourth, on <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> being overwhelmed in the Sea. The fifth, On the People of <hi>Israel,</hi> and the City of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem.</hi> And the time of the sixth Judgment is now at hand, by which God will tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulate men throughout all the Earth, with Sword, Pestilence, and Famine. Now the causes of these horrible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were first, Disobedience in our first
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39410:21"/> Parents. The second was, because Men would not be ruled by the government of the Spirit of GOD. The third, that opposing the Commandements of GOD, they committed Abominations. The fourth, Because <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not give glory unto GOD, but despised the Lord of Heaven and Earth. The fifth, because the <hi>Jews</hi> would neither hear, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Prophets and Apostles sent from GOD unto them, to exhort them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. And the causes of this sixth approaching Judgement, are, That men refuse to be obedient to the Gospel of Christ; And that these are the Times fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by our Saviour, that men should be wicked, as before the Flood, and as in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Spirit at this time repeated what before he had told him of the great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of many Kingdoms,<note place="margin">The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the Turks to make War in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
                     </note> saying, <hi>THAT HE WAS THE LORD OF THE EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERN NATIONS,</hi> and that GOD had delivered into his hands the Rod of his Judgements, and commanded him to <hi>GO ƲNTO THE WAR IN HIS OWN PERSON.</hi> The Spirit at that time also commanded <hi>Kot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39410:21"/> to declare unto all the Lords, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Potentates of the Empire, that if they would avoid the prevailing hand of this Judge, nor come into the power of him, whom GOD hath made the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioner of his Judgements; to believe that there are but two ways left them: The first, that they would repent, and believe the Gospel; and that those great Persons who have gone before the people in their sins, should now go before them in Humiliation and Amendment.</p>
                  <p>The second way to restore Peace unto the Empire, is, To promote King <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> and his Progeny. At which words of the Angel, <hi>Kotterus</hi> interposed, and said, <hi>If the King of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>and his Progeny be so acceptable, Why was he so unsuccessful as to be enforced to flye from</hi> Prague? To which the Angel did make Answer; <hi>If he had not been expelled by the Enemy, he should have been enforced from that place by some one else;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the downfal of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>but for the good of his own Progeny: who, although they are oppressed now, they shall hereafter be exalted. For I do declare unto you,</hi>
                     <q>That the Progeny of this King shall fill out unto the Pope and his Adherents, the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39410:22"/> Cup of Bitterness, which it shall be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous for them to drink.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision on the <hi>10</hi> of <hi>April, 1621.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> going out of his own House, did feel, as he thought, some hand to touch him on the right side of his Body, and to stay him. And turning his face that way, he beheld a Table triangular, of an azure colour, and three Young-men cloathed in white sitting at it, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another by the hand. Before every one of them was a Tree, about the height of an Ell in length, and on every Tree there was a Rose to be seen; when, behold a Lyons whelp leaping on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (being himself of an azure colour) taking hold of the <hi>Tree</hi> that stood to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the South, did so shake it, that the leaves did fall down with the Rose, and were turned into blood: But the <hi>Tree</hi> that was planted before the Young-Man in the North, did stand without the least moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The <hi>Tree</hi> on the East-side did appear at the first to be dry and withered; when, behold on the sodain it did flourish, and a Rose on the bough thereof, began most pleasantly to bud.</p>
                  <p>The young-Man on the North-side,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39410:22"/> holding the other on the East by the hand did say unto <hi>Kotterus, Give me the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship of thy Right Hand;</hi> and, their hands being joyned together, the young Man on the East said unto him; <hi>Be you carefull to write down all these things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly; for a great Mystery is contained in them, which GOD in a singular Vision will reveal unto you.</hi> As he spake these words, the Table, with the Trees, did vanish away; the three young men still remaining with <hi>Kotterus.</hi> And the young man of the North said unto him, <hi>Look upon us</hi> 3. <hi>with circumspection; for one of us shall return to thee again, and shall expound unto you the things which you have seen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> made answer to him, <hi>Who are you?</hi> and was so amazed, that he could not speak one word more. The young Man of the North replyed, <hi>We are the Servants of the great and dreadful GOD, but a GOD that is mercifull to you, who maketh his Angels Spirits, and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters a flame of Fire. But, do you those things which are commanded, if you will preserve the love of that great GOD.</hi> And having spoke these words, they vanished out of his sight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:39410:23"/>
                  <head>The Vision on the <hi>1.</hi> of <hi>June, 1621:</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> on that morning, having ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his window, behold there appeared to him one of those three young Men whom he saw before, sitting at the trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Table, who said unto him, <hi>Write down what I shall declare unto thee; for I am He, who sitting before on the North-side of the Table did declare unto thee, That we were the Servants of the Great and dreadful GOD,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Angel admonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Kotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> not to be proud of his gifts of Prophecy.</note>
                     <hi>but a GOD that is merciful to you. I do therefore exhort you, that you do not exalt your selfe, by reason of these Revelations that are shown unto you; nor think your selfe to be in a higher degree of Respect before GOD, above other men. For GOD respecteth not the persons of Men; but he, who believeth in him, and his Son whom he hath sent, hath everlasting life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> shall roar against the Whore of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Rome,</hi> for her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> she is now falling, but is not yet fallen, but presently shall fall. Oh thou cold, thou thirsty, and presumptuous City; it is not the height, nor the strength of thy walls shall defend thee, but they shall fall with thee. Oh! thou cold, and deceitful City, who thinkest thou stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39410:23"/> sure; Behold, the time is coming when thou shalt totter, and thy horrid lies, and false perverting of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thy great Impurities shall come to light, for the Scripture shall discover thy Spiritual Fornication.</p>
                  <p>O you Kings, you Princes, and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, who do flatter her, and drink the wine of her Impurities, and partake of the Cup of her Blasphemies, you are all like unto Her that leads you on, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; Brothers by Name, but the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the truth of God. Behold! the dry and withered Tree of the East, begins to shoot forth her leaves, and her blushing knots, but the tree of the North doth stand unmoved.</p>
                  <p>Behold! the Lion of the North, begins to rouse himself, &amp; two other of the same colour do follow him; who will pluck up that tree in the South; root, and branch. O that thou hadst known the Day of thy Visitation: But Glory be to HIM, who alone worketh Wonders.</p>
                  <p>The Spirit, on the next day returning, repeated the same words; and added, Those hundred and forty seven weeks are three weeks of the year of Jubilee, in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39410:24"/> in which a great Mystery is comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and pertaineth only to those, that are extraordinarily illuminated; but be not thou inquisitive after it, but look onely to those things, which are commanded thee. <hi>Kotterus</hi> made answer, I shall be ready and most willing to perform all things, that are commanded me, if I were sure to be believed: for there are but very few, who in these wonders will give any credit unto me. The Spirit made answer, let not that trouble you, the wayes of God are wonderfull.</p>
                  <p>There was never any made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Thoughts, and the Counsels of the Highest, but they have all been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, who would have examined the wisedome of God; for he is the Lord of Heaven and Earth, and doth all things according to the counsel of his own Wil: Look not thou after them, for they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the reach of thy understanding. Cleave fast unto the Word of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Scriptures, and the Prophets, and hear if thou hast ears to hear. How much (alas) do wilfull men mistake themselves, presuming on their own strength and power, and whispering to one another;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39410:24"/> there is no need of fear, either from the East, the North, or from the West.<note place="margin">The words of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel against the Pope and his Masse.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold a Ravening Wolfe hath hid himselfe in the East; and three Lions from the North, are coming with strength, and power, to visit the tyranny and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse of the Son of Perdition, who hath placed himselfe in his Seat, who fills both Heaven and Earth, the Man of Sin and wickednesse, the Fountain of many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities, the Master of all Corruptions in the Scripture, the Thief and Plunderer of the Honour and Glory of God; who with his own mouth hath spoke, I will not give my glory unto another, neither my worship unto Idols. And, which is worse, who poureth forth his prayers, in the intercession of Saints; and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Vigils, good Works, and Masses, for the remission of Sins.</p>
                  <p>O you corrupt Depravers of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; in which God hath revealed his Will unto you. There is no Mediator nor Intercessour, but He only, who hath declared himselfe to be so in his Word. Amen, Amen, <hi>I say unto you, whatsoever you shall aske of my Father in my Name, he shall give it you.</hi> No man, by his own
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39410:25"/> works, hath obtained Heaven nor purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his own Salvation; which consisteth onely in the pretious Merits, and the Satisfaction of the blood of the Lamb. There is no other Mediator, by whom man may be justified; but he onely, who doth justifie all that believe on him, who doth heal them by his own wounds, and conferreth Life and Salvation both to soul and body.</p>
                  <p>Do thou adhere to this thy Lord and Saviour: first, as thy Advocate, Interces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour, and Patron to his Father; who best knoweth thy own necessities, and can send thee a deliverance from them. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Adhere unto him as thy Saviour and Redeemer; unto whom all the Prophets, and the Scriptures lead thee, and to no other. Trust thou in God, and rejoyce, in his goodnesse, so shalt thou overcome all temptations; especially, if thou wilt apply thy selfe unto prayer, and the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word of God: for many false Prophets are gone forth, cloathed in Sheep-skins; whom before, I have descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to thee; who are fraudulent perverters of the Word of God. The Angel having spoke these words, disappeared.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:39410:25"/>
                  <p>After a little silence, the Angel proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>O</hi> Babylon, <hi>fair but painted, and desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of a true foundation; false is thy Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, false thy Life, and evill thy Works. Two and forty months shall quickly now be expired; and the three dayes with halfe a day shall come to an end, and the Spirit of Life shall return into those, whom thou, O wicked,</hi> Babloyn <hi>hast murdered, and the five months of thy Judgements will quickly be accomplished, and</hi> P. <hi>and</hi> D. <hi>shall fall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> did here demand of the Angel what was the meaning of the two mystical letters, <hi>P.</hi> &amp; <hi>D.</hi> The Angel made answer, P. <hi>is the Pope, the Spouse of the Devil, who doth his work for him, heaping Evil upon E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, by murders, torments, &amp; cruelties; by Adulteries, Whoredoms, and Idolatry, Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Intemperance, and Avarice, and by whatsoever the Devil, her own flesh and blood doth teach her: for behold the Devil walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among the Christians, and the Infidels; helping on the work, as the Wife is the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of her Husband: But this shall continue but for a short season.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rejoyce therefore and be glad, you who are markt with the character of the Lamb; for behold, another <hi>P. D.</hi> is coming, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39410:26"/> not yet come, and sudainly will come. <hi>P.</hi> are the horrible Plagues and punishments which suddenly wil fall on this <hi>Bridegroom</hi> and his <hi>Bride. D.</hi> is the detonating bolt of Thunder, shot from the hand of GOD, the Lightning leaping from the East, &amp; from the North for behold, the Time, Times, and Half-time, is now almost expired, and the Tramplers shall tread all things under their feet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> demanded of the Angel, <hi>Who are these Tramplers?</hi> To whom the Angel replyed; <hi>Besides the Devil, the supream Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary of the Church, there are two others, who shall destroy, and tread down all things. One of them doth not yet know the true God, but he shal know him; for the time is at hand that he shall acknowledg the true GOD, of whom he now is ignorant; and shall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plish his Decree against the great Whore sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the Hills above the Sea, who is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trampler upon, and a destroyer of the Church, whose Remembrance it come into the sight of God, to give her a cup of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candescence of his Anger. He cares not for God, neither doth God care for him; for his time is almost past, and will quickly come up unto the Number of</hi> 666.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:39410:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> again demanded of the Angel, <hi>And will there be so great an effusion of Blood?</hi> To whom the Angel answered, <hi>Yes, For, since</hi> Germany <hi>is so stubborn, as not to pray to the Almighty to with-draw hi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Rod, and heavy Hand held over it, but doth more and more provoke him; and doth so fill up the measure of her sins, that it runs over with the abundance thereof; Therefore there shall be a great Battel, and a great overthrow to the Devil and the Dragon, and a great Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per shall be prepared for the fowls of the air.</hi> Wo unto <hi>Caesar,</hi> the Kings, and Princes, the Counts and Barons. Woe unto the Countreys and Cities of the German Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. <hi>All these things shall fall upon you; Famine, and Dearth, &amp; War, and effusion of Blood; for, the Condemnation of the great Beast is near and certain. The Angel with the everlasting Gospel hath already flown through the middle of the Earth; Happy be they who shal receive it, nor despise this great treasure, by trampling it under their feet. The Sun of Righteousness shall shine upon them in his full light, and dispel these horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Clouds without any prejudice unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> interposed again; <hi>And shall the faithful be delivered from these great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:39410:27"/> The Angel answered, <hi>Rejoyce, O little Flock, thy Shepherd shall defend thee. You have in the Scriptures, most infallible promises of a certain deliverance. I shall send thee to the writings of the Prophets, and to the words of Christ and his Apostles. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Three impure Spirits have gone forth from the mouth of the false Prophet, and the Dragon, of whom beware; and drinking of the springs of living water of</hi> Israel, <hi>suffer not thy self to be drawn into the filthy lake of Frogs, in which they will be seen onely, and heard in Summer; and croaking together, they neither regard nor fear any one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> here began to complain unto the Angel, that no man would believe him; and that by declaring these Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto the world, he was fallen into great poverty, and become a scorn to all men. The Angel made answer to him, <hi>Who putteth his hand to the plough, and looketh back, is not fit for the kingdom of God.</hi> Thou hast found great favor in the sight of God. And he who wil be Gods servant, must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a reproach unto the world. Behold the time is at hand, when all these things shall be fulfilled. Do not therefore conceal these things, but be careful to perform what is commanded thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:39410:27"/>
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>August</hi> 25. 1622.</head>
                  <p>On the five and twentieth of <hi>August</hi> there appeared the two Angels to <hi>Kotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> who spake thus unto him; <hi>Kotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> our God observeth the same method which he did on the beginning of the world, he mortifieth before he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Undoubtedly you have heard the great sound we have made, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are sent as Ambassadors unto you, to inform you of more things to come. Ask what you will of us, and we will inform you. <hi>Kotterus</hi> replied, I thought I should not have seen you again, and behold I am again surprised. I receive nothing but contempt, and scorns from those to whom I make my addresses, and I conceive that there is not any one will give the least belief unto me. The Angels replied, We exhort thee to make no doubt of those things which God doth manifest by us, and our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-servants. <hi>Moses</hi> made a doubt of the breaking out of the water from the hard rock, for which he was punished by God, and entred not into the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39410:28"/> Land. Take heed therefore <hi>Kotterus,</hi> and provoke not the Almighty, lest some punishment fall upon thee also, by incurring the displeasure of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. At these words <hi>Kotterus</hi> cryed out, Lord Jesus, because I perceive that I neither can nor ought to discharge my self from this great &amp; admirable work, I wholly commit my self to Almighty God, to whom I render all humble thanks, and implore the gift of his holy Spirit; let what will become of my life, or goods, I neither fear, nor care. The Angels said unto him, This afflicteth thee, that what befalleth doth seldom befall any man, but in a short time <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> will awake from their sleeps, and <hi>John</hi> also will come forth. <hi>Kotterus</hi> said, Will <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> come again? will they be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from the dead? The Angels answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. It is not so carnally to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, as if they would rise from the dead, but that God would give his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit according to that measure which He only wise doth best know, even by us as his Angels and Ambassadors. <hi>Daniel</hi> understood not till the Angel expounded
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39410:28"/> to him, no more did <hi>John</hi> till the Angel declared and revealed to him. But the world is now grown so wise, that it thinks it doth not need the Scriptures; and if we should declare unto you any other Gospel, then the Gospel of Jesus Christ, a curse would justly fall upon us, for already it hath been done, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day it coms to pass, that by false do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and counterfeit shows, the Devil doth transform himself into an Angel of Light.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> proceeded in his discourse with the Angels, and said, They will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they have <hi>Moses</hi> &amp; the Prophets, and therefore they will reject both you and me: to whom the Angels answered, It hath been alwayes the custom of the wicked world to despise heavenly things and to esteem things that are earthly to be heavenly; but let them despise them, the Judge of the living and the dead, who sitteth at the right hand of God, whose face we Angels perpetually do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he will come and judge, and in judgement will condemn those who do not believe in Him; we declare unto you no new doctrine, nor bring unto
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39410:29"/> you any new God, but do refer you to the Scriptures, for there is no comfort without the fountains of <hi>Israel.</hi> Your own salvation, and the salvation of the whole world is not grounded on Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical revelations <hi>N. B.</hi> but who shall preserve himself from the uncleanness and infection of sin, and believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, he shall be saved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kotterus</hi> addressed himself again unto the Angels,<note place="margin">The time in which these won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful things shall come to pass.</note> and said, There is one thing more, in which I desire to be further satisfied, when &amp; in what time all these things shal be fulfilled. The Angels made answer, When you shall perceive the Heavens and the Earth to be moved with our voices, and the voice only of two shall be heard; when the voices from the East and from the North shall sound both together, then know that all these great things shall come to pass, and follow on one another. <hi>Kotterus</hi> demanded again of the Angels, If the peace made with the <hi>Turk</hi> in the East shall still continue? I told you before, that this peace should continue but for half an hour, and afterwards shall be dissolved for ever. Behold an inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39410:29"/> is rolling on, and a great tempest is coming from the North. The ravening Wolf also is coming out of his kennel in the East, who hath sharp teeth and nails, and is swift of foot: he unexpectedly will fall unexpectedly both on the shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd and the sheep, and who dares pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise security to himself?</p>
                  <p>O you Kings, you Princes and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, the most High doth laugh at your counsels,<note place="margin">The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for peace to come to nothing in the end.</note> and your treaties of peace will come to nothing; for there are no means of peace for you, then was for them of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> or for <hi>Pharaoh. Kotterus</hi> again demanded who was that ravening Wolf, and if he may not be restrained? The Angels made answer, He may with true repentance, and with fervent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. God pronounceth his judgement against a Nation or Kingdom which he intends to destroy and break in pieces: but if that Nation or Kingdom shall tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent them of their evil ways, God will repent himself of the evil which he intended to bring upon them. <hi>Nineveh</hi> was to be destroyed within forty days, but the ruin of that great City was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the penitence and amendment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39410:30"/> of the inhabitants. The King did humble himself, not saying as <hi>Pharaoh, Who is the Lord that I should hear his voice?</hi> and was therefore devoured by the red sea.</p>
                  <p>The Lion of the tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> is he who wageth war against <hi>Germany,</hi> and he doth mannage it by the Lion of the East, and the Lion of the North, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he want power or means to inflict his punishment, for which he hath many and great causes For the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Secular and Ecclesiastical, which ought to punish the pride, the impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and contempt of the word of God, do commit these sins themselves, and the Potentates of the earth do work wickedness, and, which is worse, they run whoring after other Gods, and wallow themselves in all manner of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanness, against the first and second Table. Go into <hi>Paradise,</hi> and behold the disobedience of <hi>Adam;</hi> consider, and behold the wicked works of the old world, who refused to submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the government of the spirit of God. Examine the Scriptures, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Sodom Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem,</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:39410:30"/> and you shall find, that far greater sins are now committed against God. <hi>Adam</hi> died, the old world were overwhelmed in the flood, and others were punished for their iniquities, and shall not God now strike <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Germany?</hi> consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what <hi>Daniel, Christ</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> spake of these times, that such a tribulation should come, as was never in the world before. It hath been told you, that God will punish with fire, sword and pestilence; and it hath been told you, that in the last days there will be a great defect of faith, hope and charity. If <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> had continued in the light, and not dispised it, such heavy and horrible judgements had never fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon them.</p>
                  <p>The Reader is to understand, that <hi>Kot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus</hi> had these Visions and Revelations for the space of eight years, from the yeae 1616. to the end of the year 1624. There are very many more in number besides these, declaring much horrour to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> &amp;c. and other places where sins do raign, but these may suffice at present.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="biography">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:39410:31"/>
               <head>The life and Revelations of <hi>Christina Poniatonia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Edict of <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commanding under great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties all the Reformed Ministers of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> to depart that Kingdom, <hi>Julianus Poniatonius</hi> one of the Ministers of <hi>Prague</hi> was invited to live privately with the Illustrious <hi>Charles de Zezotin, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marquisse</hi> of <hi>Moravia;</hi> He was by his Country a <hi>Polonian,</hi> and descended of Honourable Parentage, at the first a great Papist, but afterwards illuminated and converted, and a Preacher of that Doctrine which before he hated. In the year 1626. his wife died, which was the reason that he placed his Daughter <hi>Christina</hi> with the Lady <hi>Engelburh</hi> of <hi>Zelkin</hi> Baroness of <hi>Zarubia,</hi> and descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the house of <hi>Austria;</hi> where she was entertained with that respect which was due unto a Gentlewoman of her Birth and quality. For I finde after one
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39410:31"/> of her extasies (at which some persons of great Honour and Learning were often present) that as soon as she came to her self again, she did put on her chain of Gold about her neck, her Night-rayl, a Gorget on her shoulders, her rings on her fingers, and Bracelets on her arms, to make her self read to be at the rising of her Lady, who would never be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent from her, when in the day time, she had her extasies upon her, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches whereof did grievously afflict her: for sometimes as the spirit came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her she would have a cold stiffness in every part of her body, and that with so much violence that she seemed like a dead body; sometime she would be grievously tormented with Convulsions, insomuch that for a certain time she would become deaf and dumb, and blind. She began to have these Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Raptures at <hi>Branna</hi> in <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> when she was about sixteen or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen years of age, and lived with the Lady above mentioned, who at the first conceived those violent impressions to be the visitations only of some ruder feaver, and therefore sent for <hi>Labanius</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39410:32"/> and <hi>Lohmullerus</hi> two eminent profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors of Physick, to have their advice therein, who continuing with her till the hour of her Extasies transportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when they found no beating of her pulses, nor any motion of breath in her body, but a most sweet complexion in her face, which no painter with all his colors and art could parallel, they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with admiration on one another, and cryed out, <hi>Here all our Art doth cease.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was nothing omitted that might do her good, her Father was sent for to come unto her, being then so doumb, that she could not speak a word, but instead of coming himself, he did send another, which so troubled her that she did weep abundantly, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for Ink and paper she did write these words, <hi>Whai! doth my Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake me also? What can I expect from others?</hi> True it is that her Father did reprehend her in a letter to her, and did charge her to have a care of those Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions for the future, as proceeding from a phanatick distemperature; but coming himself not long afterwards, when he beheld in what extremities she was in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39410:32"/> the time of her Extasies, he could not forbear from tears, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause his Daughter did put a little paper into his hand, wherein she had wrote these words; <hi>My father, my Father, why do you harden your bowels against me, a poor worm who have the hand of God upon me?</hi> These, and some other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations like unto them, did make him altogether to alter his judgement, and returing from whence he came, he did write a little Book intituled, <hi>The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by which I am convinced to believe, that the Revelations of</hi> Christina Ponia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonia <hi>are Divine, and revealed to her from God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In many of her Visions she seemed to be rapt with an exillence of joy, in which the delights of the everlasting Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom with a faithful soul are most wonderfully and lively represented.</p>
               <p>As in the Visions of <hi>Kotterus</hi> there appeared Angels to him in the shape of young men, so in the Visions of <hi>Christina</hi> who was a virgin, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for the most part the Antient of dayes unto her in the shape of an old Man, who did reveal unto her the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39410:33"/> down-fall of the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> and of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the many other wonders, and terrible things to come now at the end of the world.</p>
               <p>After a great and fatal rapture, that was said to ravish almost her soul out of her body, and then that her recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from it was a kind of Resurrection from death, it pleased God that her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations ceased, and much about that time her Father died Her Visions were many and wonderful: she had the happy or the dreadful sight, and sense of them no longer then two years. And not long afterward, <hi>Daniel Vetterus</hi> (who taught <hi>Frederick Henry</hi> the eldest Son of the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> the <hi>Bohemian</hi> tongue) did court her in the way of Marriage, for she was beautiful both in body and in minde; and it being first propounded to the Divines of the reformed Churches in those parts, they gave their consent unto it, alledging the Example of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borah</hi> the wife of <hi>Lapidoth</hi> a Prophetess, yet married, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.4. and the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Huldah</hi> wife of <hi>Sellum,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.14.</p>
               <p>They lived comfortably together for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39410:33"/> the space of twelve years, and two moneths, and had two sons, and three daughters whom they carefully brought up in good manners, and in the fear of God.</p>
               <p>In the moneth of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1644. it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God to visit her with a great cough and a dangerous defluxion of Rheum up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her lungs, which being attended with a Hectick Feaver did translate her unto another Marriage, and to a better life, in the four and thirtieth year of her age. Her death was much lamented, and her Funerals were observed with great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. <hi>Wenceslaus Loctarius</hi> Pastor of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Church preached her Funeral Sermon, which was afterwards printed, and her History ingraven on her Monument.</p>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Visions and Revelations of <hi>Christina Poniatonia. 1627.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Her first Vision was this, which she did commit to writing with her own hand. On the twelfth of <hi>November,</hi> in the year 1627. on which day my Lady the Baroness having sent me into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39410:34"/> I beheld in the Air over the House, a Rod bound like a Broom, the handle whereof was towards the <hi>North,</hi> and the End of it was towards the <hi>South,</hi> being affrighted at the sight whereof I did run to call others to look upon it, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently afterwards it vanished away out of my Eyes, This did much amaze me, and made me very sad and melancholy, insomuch that eight dayes afterward I was visited with a great sickness, and my friends did begin to despair of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>Her vision on the Eleventh of December. <hi>1627.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Being in a great Extasie, I conceived that I was to go thorough a narrow way, and to climb up a rock so high, and steep,<note place="margin">Christina in a vision lept into heaven.</note> that I was continually afraid I should fall down from whence I came; but being come to the top thereof, I looked round about me if I could see the old man approaching to me; and lifting up my eyes I beheld the Heaven to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the old man looking down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and saying to me, <hi>Come up to me:</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:39410:34"/> but I answering, <hi>Lord, I cannot,</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Give me your hands.</hi> I therefore held out both my hands unto him, and he drew me up from the hill into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and said unto me, <hi>Pray thus,</hi> O Lord prepare my heart, and all my sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses to understand thy wonderful works.</p>
                  <p>This prayer being ended I beheld a great company, and a large plain in which they stood, so full of light that I could hardly behold it for the glory of it. I demanded therefore of the old man, what spacious and shining place it was: He answered, It is the throne and the Majesty of the living God, attend dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and behold.</p>
                  <p>And immediately upon those words, there came our of that company a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain young man having wing on his back, who clapping his wings did take an advantage thereby to lift up himself, and flying on high did cry with a loudvoice, O Lord righteous and true, wilt thou suddenly rise to take vengeance on those who with ignominy do obscure the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy name? wilt thou suddenly shine forth in the glory of thy strength to put an end to the sins of the wicked?
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39410:35"/> Arise O Lord, and shew thy self to be that God who wert in Eternity, who remainest in Eternity, and whose years do never fail. Manifest thy self to be that God in whose power is both Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and every living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and than whom there is none so faithful as thy self, and thy faithful shall rejoyce in thee, beholding thy strength, and the revenge which thou hast taken of thine and their enemies, saying, Let <hi>Jehovah</hi> the great God be magnified from generation to generation.</p>
                  <p>After he had spoken these words, he allighted on the Earth, and stood on his feet again and held his peace; I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at this Vision, but the old man said unto me, <hi>Observe again.</hi> I therefore composed my self to attention. And behold a great wind arose like the loud murmurs of a violent storm; and the thunder roared without ceasing, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Heavens did tremble, and I did quake for fear.</p>
                  <p>Then there appeared a man armed from head to foot, whose head was as fire, and a flame proceeded from his mouth: he came forth, and stood by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39410:35"/> himself, and one of the company brought him a great sword, and did put it into the right hand of the armed man, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, This is my strength, and this Right hand of my strength shall with this sword destroy all my Adversaries. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am prepared, and will come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly in a day when the wicked shall not think of me, in a day which the ungodly do not know of, and I will render unto every one according to his desert, I will put an end to all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and in my wrath I will grinde into powder all unbelievers, and cut off the Name and the memory of them from the land of the living.</p>
                  <p>But the Angel who did raise himself on his wings before, did again abandon the Earth, and flying through the Air did cry aloud with a great voice, Wo, wo, and again, Wo, wo, and more then wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those who do oppose that most mighty King; Wo unto those who most perfidiously have rebelled against that immortal King, wo unto those who have forsaken this most mighty King, for He hath forsaken them, and will forsake them, when he shall so drive them from
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39410:36"/> him, that they may never see his face in eternity. Having spoke these words he left flying, and did stand again on his feet and held his peace.</p>
                  <p>When the Armed man again lifted up his voice, and said, I will now hasten my judgement to put it suddenly into execution; but first I will perform a wonderful thing: much evil shall come from the North, and from the East upon all the inhabitants of the earth, that with a sword they shall overcome all those that proudly rebel against me, for my power, and the strength of my arm is with them, to uphold them that they shall not fall, for the heavens shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and the earth be glad, and the Sea shall laugh, and every creature shall be comforted when they shall behold the wonderful power, and the help of the Lord of glory.</p>
                  <p>Having spoke these words he vanish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from my eyes, but he who had wings, and did flie twice before, did flie again, and crying with a loud voice, he said; Rejoyce you righteous in the strength of this mighty King, for now in a short time he will arise to help you, he will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39410:36"/> multiply the gladness of your hearts with the greatness of his power, he will comfort you, and fill your hearts with abundant joy. Use but a little patience, and be assured that <hi>Iehovah</hi> the God of Hosts will perform it. Having spoke these words he disappeared, as did all the great company, at which I was struck into a great amazement.</p>
                  <p>The old man said unto me, go along with me, and I will yet show thee more. I had not gone above four paces, but I beheld a great train of Artillery, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving demanded what it was, the old man told me it was the fury of the divine wrath to be poured forth shortly upon all those who commit abominations; but the measure is not yet complete, the wickedness of the ungodly is not yet full ripe for vengeance, but the greater is the Divine, the more heavy will be the indignation of his justice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision on the <hi>13. January, 1628.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The old man having taken me by one hand, and the Lord by another, they did lead me into a pleasant garden,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39410:37"/> when behold a Lyon came running out from one part of the garden, and other Lyons from other parts, and met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one place. They were remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in their stature, insomuch that I was greatly afraid; the one of them was of an azure colour, and the other of a red, and in their fore-paw they had great swords, and sharp and long talons, they stood on their hinder feet, and in their fore-feet they did hold their swords.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Look again</hi> said the Ancient unto me, I therefore lifted up my eyes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, a white Horse of a stupendous bulk, having two heads, and holding in his fore-feet an iron Globe red hot as a coal of fire, his gate was portly and impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and he trod on the earth with so much pride, that it trembled under him. Coming near unto the Lyons he began to go but softly, as if he was afraid of them, or had a mind to go back again, but the Lyons stood over against him with great boldness, and sometimes they laid their heads together, as if they whispered something to one another, and yet they did bear a vigilant eye on the Horse; but the Horse drawing near
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39410:37"/> unto the Lyons did throw the fiery globe amongst them, hoping it would so come to pass, that whiles the Lyons were contending for the globe, he might have the opportunity to escape away; but the globe being neglected, the Lyons did set upon the Horse, did first bereave him of his two heads, and afterwards they did tear his body in pieces, and on a sudden they devoured it, and having spoken something again to one another, they threw the Bowl from them.</p>
                  <p>The Ancient said unto me, Lift up thy eyes again, which I did, and beheld a high and a broad tree standing between the Lyons, and shading them with its boughs. On the top of all the tree I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held a great Eagle sitting, having two heads, and four wings, and four feet, and two trains; and I heard the Eagle to make a great noise, but I could not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the meaning of it. I therefore asked of the Ancient, What is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that great noise which the Eagle maketh? he answered, The bird pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth these things, Behold I sit on high, being exalted above all others: who is so bold to come unto me, &amp; move me from
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39410:38"/> this high place, none is, none will be so presumptuous. But the Lyons came, and taking hold of the tree with their fore-feet, they did shake it with so much violence, that the Eagle fell down, whom they did tear in pieces, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured him, as they had devoured the Horse.</p>
                  <p>The Ancient said again unto me, come, and see yet more; and he did lead me to a great broad water, on the bank whereof there stood another great Tree, which did spread its boughs a great way. The Ancient said unto me, <hi>behold,</hi> and immediately the same Lyons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Tree did shake and throw it to the ground, they plucked up the roots of it with their paws, and threw the body, boughs and root, and all into the water, which when they had done, they made the ground level and smooth where the roots were, that there might not be the least appearance where so great a Tree did stand.</p>
                  <p>The Ancient said to me again, come, and behold the end. I came and saw a stately, great and magnificent building, most richly set forth with all the art that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39410:38"/> possibly could delight the eye. I asked the old man, what was that specious and stately building; he told me this was that proud and rebellious house, shining without, and glorious, but within full of all manner of impurities, abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and impieties; it is that great <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> whose ruine doth now draw near, for it is impossible that this house should stand any longer, because her sins and her transgressions are come up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, observe but the doom that doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it.</p>
                  <p>Immediately there came again the former Lyons, and with them a third Lyon white as snow, and coming to the house they began to demolish it, and from the foundation to overthrow it, the white Lyon assisting them with all his strength and power, until the whole building did fall down, and was turned into sands, on which the Lyons tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cried out with a loud voice, <hi>Babylon</hi> is fallen, it is fallen,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the house of <hi>Austria.</hi>
                     </note> the great house of <hi>Austria</hi> is fallen; that proud and lofty house is fallen to the ground, neither shall it ever be builded up again. That abominable and tyrannical place is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39410:39"/> destroyed, but not by our power, but by the power of the victorious Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah.</hi> After this the Lyons departed one from another, one of them this way, and the other another way, and a mighty wind arising did so disperse the sand, that nothing of it was to be seen.</p>
                  <p>The old man said unto me, Seest thou what hath been done? I answered, Yes Lord, I have seen it, but I beseech thee to instruct me what is meant by the Horse, the Eagle, the Tree, and the House.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Who are they that shall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the house of <hi>Austria.</hi>
                     </note>He answered, By that Horse, that Eagle, that Tree, and that House there is nothing else to be understood but <hi>Ferdinando</hi> the Emperour, and the Pope, and all that Devillish Anti-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Synagogue which now shall sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be cast down and blotted out of memory. The Lyons are the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> the <hi>Turk,</hi> the <hi>Tartar,</hi> the <hi>Swede,</hi> the <hi>Dane,</hi> the <hi>Hollander,</hi> the <hi>English,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Switzer</hi> and the <hi>Saxon;</hi> By these Anti-Christ and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the kingdom of Satan shall be utterly overthrown, especially that great house
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39410:39"/> of <hi>Austria,</hi> which they with all their power were not able to pluck down, were it not for the assistance of the white Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah;</hi> and you have seen how much he hath contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to it; he was a defence and a strength to all the rest, that by the virtue of his power they might always overcome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision on the twentieth of <hi>January, 1628.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the afternoon of that day I fell into an extasie, which continued five hours, and I saw, and heard as followeth. First the Ancient came unto me in a long white rayment, and giving me his right hand, said unto me, My strength and my victory be to thy eternal comfort, and to the eternal ruin and destruction of those who vainly trust in their own greatness. Come along with me, and I will shew thee a wonderful thing, for this day is a chosen day in which I will glorifie my name, and execute what I have decreed; And he said unto me, Be careful that nothing may escape your observation, for my will and my power
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39410:40"/> shall go swiftly like a flame of fire.</p>
                  <p>Suddenly after these words I beheld a mountain, on the top whereof a man standing did sound his trumpet so loudly that the earth did tremble at the voice thereof. He turned himself as he sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the four quarters of the world; and the voice of the trumpet was so ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate, that it might be understood. I heard these words; Gather your selves, gather your selves together, you Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the four quarters of the world to execute that which seemeth good to the glory of the Almighty. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held innumerable troops of horse, and bands of foot-men out of all Nations drawing themselves into two great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that were distinguished as much by their language, as by their habits, who in order and equipage of war were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialed into a <hi>Battalia</hi> one over against another.</p>
                  <p>The Lord said unto me, Observe them now; and immediately I heard the drums beating, and the trumpets sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Lord said unto me, Let us go up yonder hill that we may observe the success of the Battle more distinctly:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39410:40"/> we therefore came up to the top of the hill, on which I heard the man at the first to sound his trumpet, but the battle was fought beneath us, at the foot of the hill.</p>
                  <p>The old man said again unto me, This is the Army of the South, the Anti-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Army, the Army of the whore, and the Beast, pointing with his finger at the Southern Army, Turning himself to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he other Army, he said,<note place="margin">By the Eastern Army is alwayes meant the Army of the Turks</note> This is the Army of the East and the North, of which before I have made mention to you. Remember therefore these things which already have been declared, and observe how all things will come to pass according to the prediction. I for a long time did therefore look upon them, till at the last I observed that but few of the Nothern Army remained; the sad sight whereof did wonderfully oppress me, fearing that they would be utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, but the Ancient of Times did comfort me, and said, Behold now help is coming from <hi>Sion,</hi> from the Throne of my holiness, as often you have heard it promised; the voice of <hi>Iehovah</hi> doth command me to pronounce it, and his Word to proclaim his works.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:39410:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Look again,</hi> said the old man, and I behold a great Army descending from Heaven, which was commanded by a man in a flame, with a great sword in his hand, and he united himself and his Army to the relicks of the Army of the North. The old man said again unto me, Look up, and observe what is above thee; therefore lifting up my eyes, I beheld a fiery Arm stretched out from the Heavens, which in the hand thereof grasped a fiery sword; I beheld also clouds of smoak waving down, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the Southern Army.</p>
                  <p>The fight therefore was renewed, and the Southern Army did fall like leaves in Autumn beaten by a violent wind; some few of them remained, to whom the old man gave this imprecation, Descend into the earth, and be you mingled with the dust, you that do work iniquity. Many of the Southern Army after this were slain, and the rest fled, that not one remained of them; but the Northern Army having gained great spoils did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with joy; and the Army from Heaven ascended from whence it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended, and the arm and the sword dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeared from my eye.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:39410:41"/>
                  <p>I demanded of the old man or Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Times, who were they that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Nothern Army. He made answer, I will give you a sight of them. And immediately afterwards there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared seven eminent personages, but many more of an inferiour quality, by whom the Northern Army was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. And the old man again said unto me, In my name give them a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and declare unto them, that I will make use of their courage and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, in the restoring of my humbled to his Royal Throne. Let them not dispute which way it shall come to pass, for the King of Kings, who is in Heaven will be assistant to them. The cause is his, and he will crown it with success for the honour of his truth and name; and that the unbelieving world may be amazed at the wonders of his Almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
                  <p>After that I had delivered these words unto them, they all did fall on their faces before the Lord, saying, Who is like unto thee, O Jehovah? Who is so great a God as thou art? Thou art omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, thou art glorious, thou art eternal,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39410:42"/> thou art the only God, and besides thee there is no other. To thee, O God, the Nations do bend their knees: They do now confess thee, who before were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of thee; for thou only art the only true God, Idols are but the works of mens hands, and perish as if they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision; <hi>January 21. 1628.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Ancient said again unto me, Come, and follow me; which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I did, and was brought by them into such an extraordinary narrow place, that with much difficulty I at the last passed through it, which no sooner I had done, but an Angel with a leathern strap did ingirdle me so closely that I could not take breath; after which he bound my hands and feet, that I was not able to stir, but indeavouring to rise I fell down again on the ground, where a long time I did lye like a dead person. The Ancient of Times, and the Angels were gone from me, and I being forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and in a great distress did cry unto the Lord, Lord help me, Behold my
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39410:42"/> affliction, and make no delay, but raise me up again, I am ready to obey and glorifie thee. Help me O Lord, I am troden down, I am not able to stir. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou my contrition, and awake thou O my glory, and raise me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                  <p>I endeavoured again to rise of my self, but I did fall to the ground again, when behold, a great Brightness did inviron me, and I did stand on my feet being loosened from all bonds. On which the Angels appeared to me, of whom I did demand, To what end that was done, that I was driven into so great a strait? I desired to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand why I must be bound by them, and being forsaken to lie like a dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? I did beseech them to unfold unto me, if any danger were approching to me.</p>
                  <p>They made answer, We will expound the reason of it unto you. By that close and narrow way, and your Bonds, and sad lodging, the state in which the Church of Christ is at this present, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presented, being so oppressed under the heavy yoke of the proud <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39410:43"/>
                     <hi>Emperor</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> so bound, so weakned and forsaken, that she lyeth alone in a corner like a dead Body, having none to help her, or defend her, and being much afflicted, that those who ought to be a Help and comfort to Her, do draw back from Her to follow the multitude, and think that this ignominy thrown upon her, and this calamity which she is in, will be perpetual; they indeavour rather to trample on Her, to disperse Her, and devour Her, then to assist Her. But she not knowing what to do, continually doth humble Her self on the ground before the face of Grace with many tears and groans for Her oppression.</p>
                  <p>But God will hear Her prayers, and Her Lamentations and complaints will ascend into his Ears; for he gathereth the tears of his servants into his bottles, and numbreth all their sighs. For this saith the Creator, whose Name is <hi>Iehovah;</hi> For a little time I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken thee, but to return unto thee again with great mercy, and compassion. In a short Indignation I hid my face from thee, but in my everlasting mercy will I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39410:43"/> visit thee, for the Lord of H<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> hath sworn by his Name, saying, I will have Revenge of all my Enemies, and grind into powder all those that do rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me, which when I have perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, thou shalt be called the City of Righteousness, and my faithfull Sion. I will bring thee forth into the light, and my countenance shall shine upon thee bright as the Sun. All bonds and chains shall then fall from thee, which hardly now will give thee leave to breath; and being delivered from the violence of the wicked, and from the hands of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressour, thou shalt sing from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of thy heart, O most desired time of the most happy Messenger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision <hi>Iune</hi> 23. 1628.</head>
                  <p>I was in an Extasie for the space of three hours, and saw what followeth. The Lord came unto me clothed in such a glorious and shining Robe, that my eyes could hardly indure the splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of it, and not long afterwards fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Anti<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> whi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, before whom there did go the third person, in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39410:44"/> stature like unto them, but from the Head to the Foot like a Flame of fire.</p>
                  <p>And the Lord said unto me, Behold this day we come unto thee, to declare unto thee our Distinction in one Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and in one Equality and power of our Divinity. Thou seest here three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct persons, and yet but one true, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided, and immortal God. For the Son dwells in the Father, and the Father in the Son, and the holy Ghost in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son; and thus one God dwelleth in himself, as he hath revealed himself unto you in his most holy word.</p>
                  <p>The Antient taking me by the hand, said unto me, This day the judgements of the Lord shall be shown unto you, and his power by which he will cast down the proud from their thrones, and exalt the humble in their places. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve therefore diligently those things which now are to be revealed to you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The great desolation, to fall on the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Pope.</note>Immediately afterwards I beheld a throne, and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> siting on it. On the other side I beheld another throne lifted up,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39410:44"/> and a certaing person sitting on it, and a multitude of men about it; some of which were coming to him, others were going from him, and many humbled themselves at his Feet, and brought sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and gold unto him, and prostrating themselves, they wept and kissed his feet, to whom he gave certain papers, and commanded them to depart.</p>
                  <p>Having observed these things, I asked the Lord who He was, who had so high an estimation amongst men, that they fell down on their knees to kiss his feet? The Lord made answer to me, This is the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that cruel Beast, who arrogateth to himself Ecclesiastical and Temporal priority, and would have all things under his jurisdiction. This is the Man who troubled the Earth, and set Kingdom against Kingdom, and brought a desolation upon the world, and compelled all Nations to pay Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to him. This is that <hi>Basilisk</hi> of the seed of the <hi>Viper;</hi> the fiery Dragon flying through the earth, who enforced Kings to obey him, and who with the sparks of fire that came from him did inflame the Nations to fight against one another.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39410:45"/> This is He who calling himself a shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, was a ravening wolf, a furious Beast, and prodigy. He called him the Vicar of God in his Church, and the head of the Church, when he was indeed the Vicar of Satan, and My capital Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
                  <p>This is he who said in his heart, I will ascend into heaven, and exalt my throne above the Stars of God; I will ascend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the height of the clouds, and will be like to the most High; But God hath heard his words, and known his thoughts; therefore the most High could no longer endure it, but rouzed up Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his fury to call to an account this proud violator of his Name, and not to suffer him any more to seduce the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world; for already he hath long enough seduced them with his lies, by taking from them their Gold, and their silver, and returning nothing but empty papers, in which there is not so much as one letter written of the merits of Christe so strongly doth he possess with lies the hearts of those that do believe him.</p>
                  <p>But O unhappy man, if thou didst but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39410:45"/> know what this day will produce against thee, thou wilt lament and reproach the hour of thy Nativity. Oh unhappy <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ole, thy horn shall be taken from thee, and thy arm shall be broken, saith the Lord, thy calamity is neer at hand, and thy destruction treadeth on thy heels, It will now come, it will now come, &amp; now it is come; Lament, and condole him all you that stand by, and you who have known his Name, say, How is the strong staffe broken? how is the beautiful rod discoloured? Howl you Gates! Cry you Cities! for a fire is coming, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come upon thee, neither is there any, saith the Lord, that can avert it, or extinguish it. Descend from your glory, Sit down in sackcloth and ashes, you who believed that for ever you should govern in any Nations; for I now will shake the Heavens and move the Earth, Come thou North; make haste, O thou East, be ready at my command. Throw down those proud ones from their thrones, and break their Scepters to peices, for they are polluted with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness, and cruelty, and with all manner of iniquity,</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:39410:46"/>
                  <p>The Lord said to me again, <hi>Look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you with diligence,</hi> and I behold two very great personages, coming hastily, the one from the East, the other from the North,<note place="margin">The Turk to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the German. Empire.</note> who grapling with the Emperor and the Pope, did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw them with so much force, that the Earth trembled at their Fall, and they did tear in pieces the thrones on which they sate, that they did fly into little splinters, but they rolling in the dust did bellow forth their complaints like two Bulls, and cryed out, <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord, for thou hast rewarded us according to our works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At the same time I heard the voice as of many people How hath the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressor ceased? How hath the Tribute rested? God hath broken in pieces the staff of the wicked, and the Scepters of the Tyrants, now doth the Earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, now it is quiet; now doth Gladness clap her hands. But the Lord, and the Antient said unto me both at once, Behold now I will cease from my anger, because I have satisfied
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39410:46"/> my word and my counsel. Be silent therefore, O flesh, at the presence of the Lord Jehovah, because he hath done that which is well pleasing to him, and which his justice did decree should be accomplished.</p>
                  <p>The Lord said to me again Look again, and thou shalt see what thy eyes have long desired to behold; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately I discovered the Prince that made profession of the Gospel of Christ, who in his posterity did seem to be alive again, at which sight I was affected with much joy, and said, Thou art the Olive tree flourishing in the sight of God, and the Lord said unto him, Come forth out of dust and darkness, for I have beheld the humiliation of my pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I have observed their sighs; I have heard their prayers, and the bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their knees have been acceptable to me: But the Prince falling prostrate on his face said, O Lord Jehovah great and righteous, from thee proceeds all honour, and wisdom, and glory; I am thy servant, blessed be the Lord God of <hi>Israel,</hi> who only doth wonderful things, and blessed be the glory of his
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39410:47"/> name for ever and ever: the whole earth is filled with the majesty of his glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Turk is made the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</note>After their words the Lord did say unto me, Go unto the East, and tell the North whatsoever they have done on this account will conduce unto their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious memory, and that God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, according to whose will all these things were accomplished,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>February 9. 1628.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>After these things I beheld another man with a trumpet in his hand, who turning towards the North,<note place="margin">The dreadful devastati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Empire.</note> did found it with so much vigour, that the skies did ring again with the voice thereof, I ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Angel, who came unto me with a book in his hand, who it was. And why he did sound his trumpet so loudly? He made answer to me, It is the Angel of God, sent to call the Nations of the North, the East and the West to come against <hi>Babylon,</hi> for now is the predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated time that <hi>Babylon</hi> must fall. O how dreadfully shall <hi>Babylon</hi> be laid waste? How irrecoverably shall <hi>Aegypt</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed?
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39410:47"/> Whosoever passeth this way shall be amazed, and shall weep at the horrour of the ruine of it. Behold the day of her visitation is at hand, and of the wickedness of her inhabitants. And it shall come to pass, that he which flies from the sword shall fall into the pit, and who escapeth from the pit shall fall into the snare, and the valleys shall be filled with the carcasses of the dead.</p>
                  <p>O how dismal will be the howlings and shreiks of those whom the sword of God shall destroy? They shall cry with a loud voice O thou sword of God, how long will the edge of thy fury continue? Return unto thy scabbard, return, and be at rest: but the sword shall make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; How can I be at test, when the Lord hath commanded me to devour you? Who can turn away his hand that is stretched forth against you? O how many shall be overtaken by his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fall one upon another? The strong shall fall on the strong, and the mighty on the mighty. Every hand shall grow faint, and their knees shall knock together. This is the reward which shall be given to the enemies of the living
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39410:48"/> God, for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>February 11. 1628.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Two days afterwards the Lord himself appeared to me, and with him the Angels that brought before the book unto me: I was commanded to read ten leaves in it, which I did, and he shut the book, and departed; but the Lord continued still with me, of whom I desired to know when this destruction of the wicked should come to pass? He made answer to me, Seek not to know, <hi>how</hi> or <hi>when</hi> the wicked shall perish, but indeavour to understand <hi>when,</hi> and <hi>how</hi> the godly shall be saved: neither rejoyce you that the destruction of the wicked is at hand, but rather weep and lament that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of God cannot be diverted from there. The house of <hi>Austria</hi> shall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly fall, and the whore of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> be brought to confusion; for they have trod upon the righteous in their pride of heart, and have vainly imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39410:48"/> there is no God; wherefore God will laugh them to scorn; he will be known amongst them, and the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own pride shall fall on their own heads.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="biography">
               <head>The life and Visions of <hi>Nicholas Drabicius</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DRabicius</hi> was born at <hi>Strasnick</hi> of good parentage; his Father was a man in that City of Consulary dignity. He was ordained Minister of Gods word at <hi>Zeranick</hi> in the year 1616. at a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Synod celebrated there by the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravians, Polonians</hi> and <hi>Bohemians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was attractive in his discourse, grateful and grave in his conversation; and not stained with the least blemish that might render him unworthy of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39410:49"/> Ministry of the Gospel. He was indeed with a candor of mind without the least deceit; a love and zeal to piety, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving the least ear unto prophaness, which he no sooner heard uttered, but he would suddenly reprove it, or manifest he was displeased at it. He was incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable for his charity, insomuch that he was ready to divide his very heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those that were in necessity.</p>
               <p>In the year 1629. being turned but of the Church by his adversaries, and compelled to lead a banished life in <hi>Hungary;</hi> having abandoned all hopes of returning again to the exercise of the Ministery, he applied him to the trade of a Citizen, and was a Woollen Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; the Father of his Wife being of the same profession.</p>
               <p>And being not contented to have transgressed thus himself, he gave the same counsels unto others, affirming it was in vain, for the hope of a little relief to be contributed by other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards their uncertain mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39410:49"/> to neglect themselves by imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing wilful and extream necessities.</p>
               <p>Neither was this all, for by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versing altogether with Citizens, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to partake of their vices; and being often high in Wine he suffered himself to be carried away by the loose exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of a prophaner life, which some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times was prejudicial to him; for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning one day from a great Fair, he was in the way incountred by Thieves, who wounded him fighting in his own defence, and it is likely would have kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, if accidentally some passengers had not come in to his rescue.</p>
               <p>The Ministers of the Church of <hi>Silesia</hi> understanding of it, did admonish him by Letters to come out of the Court of <hi>Caiphas,</hi> before a necessity came upon him to lament his rashness, as it some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did on <hi>Peter.</hi> They certified him, that if he persisted to continue in the courses which he took, they should be inforced to suspend him from the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Ministery, and subject him to the discipline of the Church.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:39410:50"/>
               <p>Being startled at this sentence, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to lead a more circumspect life, and indeavouring afterwards to sell his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, there was no man found that would adventure to purchase the Estate of a banished man. And he had been taken into custody, if God had not sent a person unknown unto him to advertise him of it. Being therefore afflicted with much sadness, he returned home, where the complaints of his wife increased his sorrow. About mid-night his griefs did grow so strong upon him, that he was filled with horror, and he cryed out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, desiring him in mercy to look upon him: and immediately being rapt into an extasie, he beheld a great Army coming from the North, and a far greater army from the East, and ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with himself what should be the meaning of it, he heard a voice saying to him, Be not afraid, nor impatient, I will bring these Armies to your own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to oppress your oppressors. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amazed at this voice and vision, which hapned to me on the 23. of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> in the year 1638. knew not what should be the meaning of it, untill
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39410:50"/> the twenty third of <hi>January,</hi> in the year 1643.</p>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>January 23.</hi> in the year <hi>1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Drabicius</hi> in his sleep, seeing a great number of Ministers in <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> that had been banished their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys for their consciences, he prayed to God, being awake, that he would gather them together, and bring them home with comfort to their own Countrey; and immediately afterwards he heard a wonderful voice, and such that he never heard before; Thou desirest to return into thy Countrey, and how dost thou prepare thy self unto it. Thou disconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuest the reading of the Scriptures, which are thy guide and thy light, thy solace and thy refuge. I exhort thee therefore to redeem the time lost, and to amend thy life. He no sooner heard these words; but he cryed out, O my God, I acknowledge my iniquity, and blush in thy sight, and in the sight of men. I beseech thee grant unto thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to perform those things to which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39410:51"/> thou hast called and commanded me; I have no strength in my self at all. The voice made answer, I will comfort thee. After this he began to think with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, whether he was sleeping or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and began to feel the bed, and the walls with his hand, and to stir his feet, and move from one side to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he perceived that he was throughly awaked. Not long after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he heard the voice again, saying, My time is now come to undertake the defence of my cause, and yours, and to bring you back into your own Land. I have whispered to the East, and to the North to come up, and revenge the injuries of my servants, who cry night and day unto me; <hi>Drabicius</hi> replied, To whom shall I reveal what thou hast commanded me, it was immediately an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, To all thy brethren, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the word; <hi>Drabicius</hi> replied again, I shall become but a laughing stock unto them; and I beseech thee O Lord, to pardon me that I presume to speak unto thee, and to be informed, by whom we shall be delivered.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39410:51"/> delivered; It was answered, The East and the North shall obey my call; I will cause the Turke to come up, and to overthrow <hi>Vienna;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Turke to come up and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                     </note> as <hi>Jerusalem</hi> was overthrowne: For there doth <hi>Pharaoh</hi> dwell: There my name is trod upon, and my Righteousnesse despised: There, all Impiety and Prophanenesse have increas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the heighth. Wo be unto them! For they have thrown the Scriptures behind their backs, and despised my holy Law. Do you not remember, that <hi>Assur</hi> was the Rod of my Anger, and the Staffe of my Indignation; as now the House of <hi>Austria</hi> is: I have broken that, and I will break this; for now the time approacheth. <hi>Drabitius</hi> replied, What shall be the Condition of us in our own Country? such as it was before? The answer was, That is determined by my Counsell, which you hereafter shall see. The Land, in which you live, shall be horribly laid waste, but a Relique shall be saved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>Jan. 31, 1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Write, That the time is now come, wherein, I will revenge the offences, given to my Holy Name, and I will
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39410:52"/> bring evill upon the House of <hi>Austria</hi> to cut it off from the Earth: for she hath given no Ear, to the peaceful counsells of the King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> who therefore is now angry with her, and shall therefore look upon her a far off, when her destruction approacheth. <hi>Drabitius</hi> asked, when will this come to passe? It was answered, <hi>This day and to morrow, will fill up the measure of her iniquities; and I will bring many great and strong Nations upon the House of</hi> Austria, <hi>and they shall tread upon</hi> Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; <hi>as</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>and</hi> Samaria, <hi>were trod upon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vienna</hi> to be tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon, as <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and <hi>Samaria.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>to revenge my quarrell, and to drive away Idolaters, with the false prophets, and to vindicate the injuries offered to</hi> Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick, <hi>that was King of</hi> Bohemia, <hi>and to his Progeny, with whom you also have been banished. Drabitius</hi> said, and shall the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> be restored to their Dignity?<note place="margin">The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</note> It was answerd, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have I afflicted</hi> Germany, <hi>but because they did abandon him: and your Land also shall suffer, because they abandoned him. Wo to the</hi> Bohemians; <hi>Wo to the</hi> Selesians; <hi>Wo to the</hi> Moravians; <hi>for now their destruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is at hand: and although there be some there, who do know my Name, yet they are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39410:52"/> wanting who should forewarn them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision. <hi>Feb 14. 1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Go tell thy Brothers, and charge them to cry aloud and knock at the doors of my Mercy; for as a Father knoweth the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of his Children, and yet will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by them; so also do I know of what things you stand in need: let them make no doubt of the Power of my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>Drabitius</hi> replied, O Lord God, the words I speak, are suspected, by those to whom I do declare them; for they say, I am deceived, and what I speak, is not the voice of Him, who hath created us, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, &amp; sanctified us; who spake by the Patriarchs; by his own Son; and by the holy Apostles; but that being seduced my self, I goe about to seduce others. It was answered to me: What I have done heretofore, what I do at this present, and what I will do hereafter, is best known unto my selfe: It is my Counsel, and they are my Judgements, and not the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men, who of necessity are to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to those things, which I now do, &amp; will performe: for who was he that was before me, &amp; who is he that shall come after me? whom have I need of to teach me, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39410:53"/> the secrets of all hearts, which no man knoweth better then my self, who am the Maker of the heart, for nothing is hid from me, neither is this thing hidden from me, what Consultations are on foote and what combinations made, to frustrate that which my right hand hath decreed to do with the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> which I will shake and make to totter with my Judgements.</p>
                  <p>Go, tell the Prince of <hi>Transilvania,</hi> that he must desist from his Counsels, and fulfil my decrees to contribute to the Destruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> with her Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.<note place="margin">An ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to joyn with the <hi>Turk,</hi> and <hi>Tartarian</hi> against the House of <hi>Austria.</hi>
                     </note> Doth he feare to be seduced? Bid him not be deceived, but call to his Assistance, the <hi>Turke,</hi> the <hi>Tartarian,</hi> and the <hi>Moscovite,</hi> or the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia;</hi> he shall find that none of them will refuse him, for I will draw those and other Nations to his side, Nations which he hath not known, but whom I know. <hi>Drabitius</hi> answered, Lord God Jehovah, How shall I execute these things, being but a poor and a contemptible person? and by whom? For these Kings are above me, and I am afraid of them: Answer was made by N. N. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:39410:53"/>
                  <head>The Vision <hi>Feb. 27th. 164<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The word of the Lord came to me again, a little before I fell a sleep; and as soon as I awaked, behold a swift Spirit came out of my mouth, and I trembled all over for fear; and I heard a voyce say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, and do you doubt also of the truth of these things, which I have reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you? The Interpretations of divers other persons are not unknown unto me, but take heed that you be not seduced by any one, for I will repeat what I have said before. <hi>The time is now approaching in which I will grind to pieces the House of</hi> Pharoah, <hi>and utterly overthrow the House of</hi> Austria <hi>to the performance of which Work, I will call many Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation on the <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> in the Year <hi>1643.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>On the twenty eighth of the said Moneth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the House of <hi>Austria</hi> unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</note>
                     <hi>I on a suddain felt a great prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my right side, and I heard a voyce,</hi> This pain is from me, and it shall continue on thee, untill thou hast declared those things to <hi>N. N.</hi> for I am not changed, neither will I be changed in any thing which I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that shall come to passe against the House <hi>Austria,</hi> by the Eastern, and the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39410:54"/> Northern Nations, for he made my Laws; of no account, and did cast my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments behind his back. What I have said already, I will speak again. Be not afraid, for I will thoroughly perform what I have begun; for I will overthrow the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> for the time draws near which I have appointed, I and no other, for no man can resist my Counsells, it is my businesse, and who shall contradict my Counsells?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>June 11th. 1644</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hungary</hi> to fall off from the <hi>German</hi> Emperour.</note>Hear the voice, O House of <hi>Austria,</hi> thy roots are in <hi>Hungary,</hi> which I am going now to pluck out; but thou shalt perish with thy Captains, thy Counsellours, and thy Posterity: Thy Strong men shal fal, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation <hi>April 7. 1646.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>As I awaked out of sleep, scarce master of my senses, a voice sounded in my ears; <hi>O</hi> House of <hi>Austria, O</hi> thou House of <hi>Austria,</hi> I have born thee, &amp; born with thee, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages, I have advanced thy glory on high, in the midst of many nations; with much longanimity of Patience, I expected thy conversion unto me, to me thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. But, thy heart is grown fat, and thy eys are darkned, that neither thy self, non thy Captains, should see their lamentable fall,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39410:54"/> and ruine, which I have denounced on thee, for the abominations thou hast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; thou, and thy Captains, and thy Counsellours, who did seduce thee with lyes, and flatteries. O House of <hi>Austria,</hi> thou hast forsaken me, and thrown my Laws behind thy back, and refusedst to read them or to hear them; but thou hast erected Idols of Abominations through thy Cities and Streets; and in thy Temples, and Chauncels, thou hast set up Statues and Images, gilded and painted with beautiful colours. Thou with thy Counsellours, thy Judges, and Princes, hast neglected my Word, and trampled on Justice, Righteousnesse, and Mercy; therefore have I brought evill upon thee, and thy House, by stirring up many strong Nations against thee; over which thou shalt not prevail, untill they have utterly rooted thee out, and thy posterity with thee. In vain, thou leanest on a Reed,<note place="margin">Vain will be all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations from <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     </note> which is the House of <hi>Spain.</hi> In vain, thou expectest assistance from the <hi>Pope.</hi> The <hi>Bavarian,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Saxon,</hi> and both <hi>Mentz</hi> and <hi>Cullen,</hi> will deceive thee: for they have lost their strength with thee; for I have risen up against them, and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39410:55"/> their powers into their hands who do make War against thee; that they may do to thee, as to the House of <hi>Ahab;</hi> and to thy Priests, as my servant <hi>Elias</hi> to the Prophets of <hi>Baal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having heard these words, I pondered a little with my self what answer to make; For as often as the Lord pronounced these words, <hi>O House of Austria,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them with so great a severity, that I trembled to hear him. After a little pause, I said unto him, <hi>Pardon thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, if I aske thee, Wherefore, thou reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est such things to me?</hi> He answered; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I have chosen thee to call those Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as with a Trumpet, which I have stirred up against the House of</hi> Austria, <hi>and those wicked Idolaters; and that they may not fail in the Execution of their Charge, untill they have rooted out of the Earth that Progeny of Vipers, and restore my Worship into the purity of it, as did</hi> David, Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>and</hi> Ezechias <hi>my faithful servants. And let all those Nations know, that they also with their Armies, are included in my power: But as long as they shall keep my Laws, and observe my Statutes, and my true Worship, and observe good Order,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39410:55"/> with mercy, all things shall go well with th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. But they must not imitate the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and Cruelty of the House of</hi> Austria, <hi>which destroyed the Temples in which my Name was celebrated, banished, and scattered those that worshipped me, and put many of them to Death; and by their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Rapine brought a great Desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on their own Countries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>Octob. 10. 1646.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The word of the Lord came unto me again, saying;</hi> Although it be not yet come to pass, which not long since I declared to you, yet undoubtedly it shall take effect. You that have gone unto the Prince, and signified my Will unto him, have done well in it. But because the Prince with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellours would not understand it,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction o<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire must begin in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
                     </note> but made a Peace, he hath gained nothing by it, but the delay of a little Time; which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelesse shall come, and is even at hand; for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is already come to the shoar of the Sea, and his Counsellours know not what Counsel to administer to him; for the destruction of the Beast must begin in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:39410:56"/>
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>June 14. 1647.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I will bring my Cogitations to an end, which I have revealed to you. Fly from the East, the North, and the South, and flock together to destroy <hi>Assur,</hi> with <hi>Moab;</hi> for now the Hammers and Hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, and Spades, and Pick-axes are ready for the pulling down of <hi>Vienna.</hi> All things are ready; the very Gates are open, and it is I that forbid them to be shut; and I will forbid it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>Nov. 5. 1647.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>When it was every where reported that the Prince was dead, &amp; it was very certain that it was so; <hi>Drabritius</hi> being awaked out of his sleep, and full of horrour, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Almighty God, that, remembring his mercies, and promises made to him, he would take away his anger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>Decemb. 4. 1647.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the morning, after his first sighes and prayers to Almighty God, a Voyce came unto <hi>Drabritius</hi> from the Lord, saying, <hi>I am glad of it; for the Terminations of the time are now fulfilled. I have now thrown the strength of</hi> Pharaoh <hi>into the Sea; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39410:56"/> can that smoaking Firebrand the Pope, nor that broken Reed the Spaniard, on whom he so confidently relyed, do him any good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>May 2. 1651.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It is my pleasure, <hi>saith the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">By the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stern Army the Turk is alwayes understood.</note> That the Eastern Armies shal be sent to strike a terrour into the great Beast; which when the Inhabitants of the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>West</hi> shall behold, they shall take courage to remove those throughout all <hi>Germany</hi> from their Thrones and Dignities, who did flatter and uphold the Beast in his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but let them bring with them that Ingenuous Lyon from the House of <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> the late King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>Nov. 21. 1658.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Turke</hi> also shall wonder at this work of mine: write therefore to <hi>Adjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Bible to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into the Turkish tongue, and to be given to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the Turks.</note> a chosen Vessel of Grace, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that the Law of my Word be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into the <hi>Turkish</hi> Tongue; and that the Book be sent to the <hi>Turkish</hi> Emperour. I will rejoyce in this work, that my Word shall be revealed to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> But be you of good Courage, and rely on my protection, which shall be present with you. Fear none but Me, and perform the Will of your Creator. Be not drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39410:57"/> by any man, to do anything against my will; for your Judgements are not as my Judgements, and it is impossible for you to search into my works. It is better for you to be silent, and to rely on me, than to be curious what I will do with this man, or that man; with this Kingdom, or that Nation. For neither the Angels, my servants, although they be alwayes with me; neither do the Spirits, know more than what I reveal unto them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="revelation">
                  <head>The Revelation, <hi>March 10. 1652.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Drabitius</hi> having his thoughts troubled within him all the night, in the morning the voyce of the Lord came unto him, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Howl, O howl, thou cursed House of <hi>Austria,</hi> weep and lament; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Arrows of my wrath are flying over to thee, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> I have powred forth from my Throne, to revenge thy iniquities and thy tyranny which thou hast exercised o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Nations committed to thy charge, and over the people who have upheld thee, and maintained thee. Thou, O House of <hi>Austria,</hi> hast made thy self drunk with the blood of many excellent illuminated persons, who have served thee, and given thee good Counsel; but thou hast enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39410:57"/> them from the Land, and Inheritance of their Fathers, raging in thy cruelty, until the day and hour of thy Ruine, which I have appointed for thee; for thou didst ride upon the Beast, and the Beast on thee, commanding thee to murder thy Subjects, pull down their Cities, and lay waste their Countries, without any fear of God, or compassion of Man: therefore now the time is come of thy lamentation; for I have heard the cry of the Souls of the slain for my Word, crying under the Altar of my Merit. Fly therefore, you Nations of the World, and assemble your selves together to the Supper of my Anger. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the flesh of the slain without mercy, for the Beast hath filled up the measure of her sins upon the Nation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="visions">
                  <head>The Visions, <hi>June 5. 1662.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Lord shewed to <hi>Drabitius</hi> the Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of certain Magistrates, and the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which they gave on a Woman very tall, but deformed. One of them did put an Axe into the hand of <hi>Drabitius,</hi> and said unto him, <hi>Cut off her head;</hi> which he did, although full of fear; and she did
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39410:58"/> fall to the Earth with so great a violence, that he was much affrighted at it; and waking, he prayed. And the Lord said unto him, This is that Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> drunk with the blood of the Saints, which I have given to thee to be executed in the sight of the world; which indeed is not yet fallen, but which shall fall, when ever that half-dead person shall fall, with the <hi>House</hi> so known unto thee.</p>
                  <p>And, after a long silence, the Lord said to me again; All my words shall be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that it may be manifest unto <hi>All,</hi> that I am HE who do Speak and Do, who will confound the Counsels of my enemies, and will remove that half-dead person from his <hi>Throne,</hi> by electing to me that chosen Vessel, the King of <hi>France:</hi> for whom, <hi>Germany</hi> shall cry out,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>France</hi> to contribute much to the Liberties <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>VIV AT, VIV AT, VIV AT REX FRANCIAE, Long live, Long live, Long live the King of</hi> France. Which as soon as it shall be done by my Command, who am King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and whose Name is Immortality; your former Liberties shall be restored to you throughout all the WORLD, O you Worshippers of Me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:39410:58"/>
                  <head>The Vision, <hi>Aug 8. 1654.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It shined very light in the morning, when the Lord shewed to <hi>Drabitius</hi> a great Tub, full of Water; whose Hoops did break, and the water did run out; when (behold) a company of lusty men, running to stop the Vessel, did indeavour to put on new Hoops; but in vain, for the water began to run out more violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on every side: they therefore lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongst themselves, they had not looked to it before. <hi>Drabitius</hi> wondred at them all the while, to see them so vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lose their labour; and pondering with himselfe what may be the signification of it, the Lord said unto him; <hi>Write,</hi> I have shewn thee, the Great Tub, into which the Nations of the Earth were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and I reduced them into one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for the performance of my work, of which the Southern Parts have but little understanding, but they shall be taught by the <hi>Western;</hi> for behold no Hoops nor bounds of humane capacity, nor all the Counsels of my adversaries shall be any impediment to me: that my Resolutions
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39410:59"/> against <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Whore sitting on the Beast, shall not proceed: Behold, how in this Land, they combined and spoke Counsels together, to put a stop to the great work which I have in hand; but all in vain: For my Armies shall break forth upon them like a Deluge, neither shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man say: <hi>How is this done?</hi> but onely, <hi>THE TIME OF DESTROY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING, AND ROOTING ƲP, IS COME;</hi> which they, who throughout all <hi>Europe</hi> were afflicted by Antichrist, did earnestly expect. Happy be they, who taking the Plagues out of my hands shall throw them on the wicked and ungodly. You O Kings, Princes, and Commanders of my Army, &amp; you my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the Ministers of my Gospel; Throw your net into the Sea, not onely on the right side of you, to fish for the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the reliques of the fruites of my Summer, the Remainders of my Vintage; but on the left side, on the Nations of <hi>Turkey,</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Turks and Tartars as well as the Jews to be converted.</note> and other places beyond the Seas; For I have opened my prisons, and healed your wound, that you may be admitted to the Banquet in the House of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39410:59"/> my Church, where you shall be fed with hid treasures. Happy be they, who according to my Commandment shall give you this food. You are now come within the doors of the times appointed by me. Excellent are the things, and above the reach of your understandings, which I do offer by my witnesses.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <head>The Vision of <hi>Drabicius</hi> concerning the Jews and Turks.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Drabicius</hi> in a Vision beheld a most stately house, in which were many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, in one whereof sate a Princess ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable for her beauty; and he heard a voice saying to him, My servant, I have shewed you my house on Earth, which is my Spouse the Church. Many rooms in it are yet empty and void of those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons which ought to be brought unto it, and those are the <hi>Iews</hi> and the <hi>Turks,</hi> and many other paople ignorant of the worship of the true God, and the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of the Lord Jesus, who are now all to acknowledge me, and to come within the pales of my beloved Spouse.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="vision">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:39410:60"/>
                  <head>The Vision concerning the calling of the Jews, and the Government of the Church after the destruction of the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> and the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Lord said unto <hi>Drabicius,</hi> The time is now come that I will renew the face of the Earth, and begin it with the people of the <hi>Iews:</hi> and it is my will to have their fabulous Books taken from them and burned among all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons throughout which I have dispersed them; and that they shall be informed by the Ministers of my Gospel in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise of the true Religion, and that those who continue obstinate amongst them shall be put to death without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.<note place="margin">The rules for Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists.</note> The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> may be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Communion of the Church but on this condition, that for the time to come they do not seperate themselves from the body of it, but frequent the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and hear there the appointed Pastors, according to the <hi>Rite</hi> of Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical succession; for I am the living God, and I will be worshipped with unanimity of heart by all that serve me. I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39410:60"/> no more Sects nor Divisions in the whole world: I will have a Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongst the Idolatrous Ministers of the whore, and those that shall be found to be refractory shall be put to death without mercy, for I will not have the least root left of the Papal Doctrine in any Nation. And after the destruction of the Beast, I will that there be but One Order and Government of the Church amongst all Nations, and that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Gospel be One in Life and Doctrine, and Rites of Displine, and that the Bishops and Pastors have Wives, and that considerable maintenance in every Church be provided for them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The chief scope of all these Revelations being to invite men to attend the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God in his punishments of the sins of the world, and to be worthy of his mercies, which in this last Age he will pour fourth on all mankind; it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come us mutually to admonish one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to repentance, and to increase our Faith in the promises of God, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our mutual charity to pray for one another, &amp; all for all, that we may all be made partakers of so unspeakable a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy:</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>